<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true report of all the doynges at the assembly co[n]cernyng matters of religion, lately holden at Poyssy in Fraunce.  Written in Latine by Mayster Nicholas Gallasius, minister of the Frenche Churche in London, and then present, [and] one of the disputers in the same, translated into English, by I. D.... Seen and allowed accordyng to the order appoynted by the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
            <title>True report of all the doynges at the assembly concernyng matters of religion, lately holden at Poyssy in Fraunce.</title>
            <author>Des Gallars, Nicolas, ca. 1520-ca. 1580.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846357</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 215:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true report of all the doynges at the assembly co[n]cernyng matters of religion, lately holden at Poyssy in Fraunce.  Written in Latine by Mayster Nicholas Gallasius, minister of the Frenche Churche in London, and then present, [and] one of the disputers in the same, translated into English, by I. D.... Seen and allowed accordyng to the order appoynted by the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                  <title>True report of all the doynges at the assembly concernyng matters of religion, lately holden at Poyssy in Fraunce.</title>
                  <author>Des Gallars, Nicolas, ca. 1520-ca. 1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[136] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules Churchyarde, by Luke Harryson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Nicholas Gallasius = Nicolas Des Gallars.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation of the proclamation of safe conduct for those attending the assembly dated 25 June 1561 (greek cross 6-greek cross8).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The doinges at Poyssye in Fraunce.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; much of translator's last name cut out of title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [greek cross] A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>Jonathan Blaney</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE report of all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges at the aſſembly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng
matters of Religion, lately holden at Poyſſy in Fraunce.</p>
            <p>Written in Latine by Mayſter Nicholas Gallaſius, miniſter of
the Frenche Churche in London, and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; one of the
diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in theſame, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Engliſh, by. I. D.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Seen and allowed accordyng to the order appoynted by the Queenes
Maieſties iniunctions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the ryghte honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Lord Frauncis Ruſſel,
Earle of Bedford, and one of the Queenes Maieſties priuye councell, Nicholas
Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mmediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my retourne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thys Realme, (ryghte
honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) I thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, than to ſhewe the cauſe
of my lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g pylgrymage. That bothe all menne maye vnderſtande, why I haue bene
ſo long abſente from my churche: and alſo what was the ende of that
aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye, where I was, and eke what fruite, I reaped of my trauayle
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For I vnderſtande, that ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye rumours haue bene ſpred
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that manye haue eaſilye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded themſelues, that whiche
they moſt deſired.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:3"/>So that in theſe oure tymes I fynde it moſt true,
which long ſynce was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Namely, that the people iudgeth, and now
meaſure moſt thyngs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to there owne opynion, and very fewe
accordyng to the truth. Whiche foolyſhe iudgements to withſtand, I counted
it paine well ſpence, not onely by word of mouth, to certifie my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and
familyers, but alſo to put in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to the ſight and reading of al
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the late doinges betwixt vs, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates at Poyſſye. Whiche as
ſymply &amp; playnelye: ſo I proteſt to doe truly and faythfullye. As
they themſelues, which were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te at the doynge therof, can
witneſſe. Great, ſure was the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of this aſſemblye and
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference. And not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out cauſe. For neuer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fore in Fraunce were we
quyetlye heard, or admitted to the defence of our cauſe: but rather without
cauſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, banyſhed and impryſoned. Now therefore it was no
maruell, yf with thys ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and ſodayn chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, mens myndes were in
greate expectacion, &amp; had conceyued good hope. Eſpeciallye, foraſmuche
as the truthe ſhyneth of it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, <pb facs="tcp:11319:3"/> &amp; waxeth ſo much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
more mighty, as men with greate force and ſuttelty, aſſay to
ſuppreſſe it. But they muſt not thynke, that we were heard of them,
which were dryuen thereto for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part agaynſt there willes, &amp;
altogether enforced thereto, by the neceſſirye of common commaundemente.
For they woulde alwayes, either haue vs put to ſylence, oure mouthes
ſtopped, or els referred to there greate God at Trent: only neceſſitye
therefore made vs au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Bycauſe no otherwiſe, the feare of imminent
peryls could be repreſſed, nor they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues which hate vs moſt, haue
prouided for their own quietnes. Wherfore, al be it they fayned, that they were
wiling to come to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, yet they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued with vs only ſo long, as
they hoped in the meane tyme, they myght well content the Kynge and the nobles,
and appeaſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons. For to leaue of the ſeueral diſcourſe, al
theyr doinges generally, but chiefly their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, whereby they brake the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly diſcloſed, what their purpoſe was. Whiche if
we conſider, certainly we ſhall maruell that we dyd <pb facs="tcp:11319:4"/> ſo often
come to talke, and wer ſuffred ſo long to pleade our cauſe. But w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out
reſpecting the councels or iudgements of men, we muſt weye the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
of God, wherby he preuenteth al perilles, and geueth a happy and lucky ende, to
doubtfull beginninges. For god which neuer faileth thoſe that are his, hathe
farre exceded our hope and expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For who thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> albeit we wer
ſent for, yet many beyng vnwilling, &amp; ſome ſtriuing againſt it, we
ſhould, be heard at all, who ſawe not a thouſande wyles prepared for vs,
wherby we myghte eyther be put to death or ſilence? After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we weronce
heard with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great grudge of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops, who wuld haue hoped, for the
ſeconde, or third meetyng? Who thought not, that, we were led, as
pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to pleade oure cauſe? And where as moſte vniuſte condityons
were offered vs whereby the Byſhops mynded to ſhame vs, and win
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a glorious victory: who thought not that we woulde ſtreyght
haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and hauing ſo good occaſyon offered vnto vs, woulde
foorthwith reaſſe from conference.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:4"/>Yet we choſe rather to abyde al pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles, yea, and
to muche wrong, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than we woulde geue any occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to breake of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
conference. We gaue vp a confeſſion of oure fayth, that is to ſay, of all
the churches in Fraunce that profeſſe the ghoſpell. To maintain and
defends theſame, we wer alwayes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Or if the biſhops would haue
ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth any of theirs, we promiſed ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conferre therof: &amp; to
confute it, if ther were in it any thyng, not agreable to the woorde of God.
But we coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer get them together withoute great entreatye, or continuall
callyng on them. At the laſte, when they neyther coulde nor durſte, openly
to breake of the conference, once begonne by the Kyngs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, they
thoughte good by litle and litle, to looſe, &amp; breake of. For firſte
from the great audyence, in the whiche we were firſt heard wyth greate
companye, reſtrained in a more narowe place, we were admitted onely to the
number of .xii. where they had a greate companye of their monkes and doctours.
Neither yet did this order pleaſe them long.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:5"/>For at the laſte, the matter was refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to fiue
on ether part, and yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, thoſe that wer choſen for them
bicauſe they wer graue and quiet men, they ſaid, wer neuer appoynted
therto, by their conſent. For they thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to much bent to peace &amp;
concord, which they hate. All theſe pollicies, attempted (as it ſemed in
vayn) without any aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere geuing vs, or any parte of theyr mindes
ſignified vnto vs, they depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But although this labor may ſeme
emploied in vain, wherof their apeares eyther no end, or els no certain
conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: yet neuertheles herby is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to al men, howe great
is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of truth, which can be ſuppreſſed by no might of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by no
wile, nor guile. For ſhe feareth her aduerſaries, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth her
defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders and patrones &amp; maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be feared, albeit thei are few and
ſmal of force: ſhe vanquiſheth and rooteth out all error, be it neuer
ſo depe rooted: ſhe detecteth and chaſeth deceites and lies, euen as the
light with her beames doth the darkneſſe: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, although manye
yeares, ſhe hath lien hydden and ſuppreſſed, yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt
<pb facs="tcp:11319:5"/> ſhe becomes vanquiſher of all her foes. Which foraſmuche as
the lorde dailye proueth before our eyes, truely we are vnkinde, and
vnthankefull, vnleſſe we mindefully weye it. Leaſt therefore the fame of
theſe doynges ſhould dye, leaſt they ſhuld be falſified with lyes, or
blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with falſe tales, immediately after my retourne, I wrote the note
thereof, and deſcribed all thynges euen as they wer done. But whiles I
doubted, vnder whoſe name I might beſt publiſhe the ſame, your honor
cam forthwith to my minde, to whom for great fauoure and gentleneſſe I am
much bounden, and not I onely, but as many els, as beyng true worſhippers of
god, are fled hither for religion. To your highnes therfore, I haue dedicated
the ſame, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foraſmuch as you are muche enflamed with the deſire of
godlineſſe &amp; religion, and wiſh the baniſhment of error and deceit,
you may hereby plainly ſe, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in our realme of Fraunce,
howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel encreaſeth ther, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; modeſty, we
ſuffred our aduerſaries and alſo what hope we may conceue, of thinges to
come. Neither can I wyth <pb facs="tcp:11319:6"/> ſilence ouerpaſſe, how much the
exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the happy and quiete gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this flouriſhing realme, and
the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of all the nobles of this realme that fauoure the goſpell,
and chiefly of the moſte noble and gracious Queene Elizabeth, hath ayded vs
to ſtoppe the mouthes of our aduerſaries, which are alwayes wont to obiect,
that with the chaunge of religion, the chaunge and diſorder of the realme
will likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. For bothe hye and lowe would laye vnto them the
example of this floryſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing realme, whoſe ſtate hath neuer ben more
quiet, than ſince the times that the moſt noble Queene Elizabeth,
reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red religion defaced by her ſiſter to the auncient puritie and
ſinceritie. For, what may more winne the fauour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to the Prince,
than pure religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and zele of truthe. Then at the laſt doe men perfectly
knowe theyr duetyes to their Princes, when firſt they knowe their duetye to
God, by whom Princes are appointed as vicars or lieuetena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts And thoſe
thynges whiche your honor yet ſayde and reaſoned, touchyng thys argumente,
and the mayntaynyng of <pb facs="tcp:11319:6"/> true religion, when you were ſent into
Fraunce to congratulate oure Kyng, yet ſticke imprinted in the mindes of
many. Neyther haue ye left any ſuttle ſpurres or prouokementes to vertue,
in the mindes of ſuche as are Godlye, with the preſident of youre vpryght
ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, gentleneſſe, liberalitie, and youre true and ſincere Zele,
whereby when I perceiued, that thei prouoked and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, wiſhed ſo
well to your honor as they ought. I thought I ſhould plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them alſo,
if to you, whome I knowe to embrace and defende al godlineſſe, I ſhould
preſent theſe newes, whiche bothe to all men, but chiefly to ſuch as are
patrones and defenders of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth, ought well to bee knowen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:7"/>
            <head>¶ The proclamacion of ſummons and ſaue conduit, to the
generall conſultation of the clergy in Fraunce. Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated out of Frenche
into Engliſhe.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES, by the grace of God king of Fraunce,</signed>
               <salute>to al our Baylis,
Stewards, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſtes, Iudges or their Lieutenauntes &amp; other oure
Iuſtices &amp; officers, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhal apertaine, Greting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, whiche we preſentely cauſe to be made,
of the Prelates of our Realme, for the cauſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the Letters which
we haue heretofore written vnto them, it hath ſemed to vs right requiſite
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al our ſubiects which concernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cauſes ſhall <pb facs="tcp:11319:7"/>
haue any thinge to ſaye, or that will be heard in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie,
may there be and appere in all ſafetye, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope that we haue by this
meane to receiue a good and holy reſolution: For thys cauſe we by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
aduiſe of our moſt honored Lady and mother the Queene, of our moſte dere
and moſte beloued vncle the king of Nauarre, of the princes of our bloud, and
other Lordes of our Counſell, haue permitted &amp; doo permit by theſe
preſentes, to all our ſaid ſubiects, of what eſtate qualitie or
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ſoeuer they be, whiche ſhall haue, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boueſaid, any thing
to ſhew, may ſafely, freely, and without any feare, come, appere and be
heard in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid aſſemblie, which we make to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here nere vnto vs
in our town of Poyſſy, <pb facs="tcp:11319:8"/> and there to tary and ſoiourne ſo
long as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhall endure, and afterwarde to returne and depart in like
ſafety &amp; libertye, where and as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſeme good. And to this
ende we haue by theſe preſentes geuen &amp; doo geue to them good and
lawfull ſurety, moſt expreſſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng all perſones whatſoeuer
they be, our ſubiectes or other, not to miſdo or miſſay in dede nor in
worde, in any ſort what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, to them that ſhall come, as is
aforeſaid, to the ſaid aſſemble, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> * with. Enioyning
likwiſe to thoſe our ſaid ſubiectes which ſhall come for this
entente, that vpon like paines, they behaue and order the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues mildely
&amp; modeſtly, &amp; without ſtirring vp any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or ſeditions. And
to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende <pb facs="tcp:11319:8"/> that this our preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, will, and
entent may be open &amp; manifeſt to all men, we will &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund you by
theſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receite therof, ye cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be red
and publiſhed in all places of your aſſemblies accuſtomed to make cries
and proclamacions, to the end that no man pretend excuſe of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and
that they which ſhal haue cauſe to be at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly may be
&amp; appere there in tyme.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Geuen at Sainct Germaines in Laye <date>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxv. day of
Iuly in the yeare of grace M. D. Lx. I. and of our reigne the fyrſt.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By the King.</signed>
               <signed>Roberte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:9"/>
            <head>¶ A briefe reherſal of the doings at Poyſſye,
betwixt the Lordes of the ſpiritualty, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel.
Set forth by M. Gallaſius.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there hath bin in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce theſe many yeares, great
ſtrife and contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hath cauſed muche cruelty to
be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed towardes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: at the laſt, when the authors thereof
perceiued, that their puniſhmentes little profited, and that thintentes of
ſuch as were Godly, were therby neyther alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nor diminiſhed, they wer
compelled to aſſaye more gentle meanes, farr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke the firſt. Therefore
in the yeare of our Lord God. 1561. Charles, the ninth of that name, a Prynce
of ſynguler to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlyneſſe, and of great hope, then reigning, the peres
of the realme myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded tymely to withſtande the peril like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enſue in
ſo great a diſcorde. For now, their number encreaſing whyche <pb facs="tcp:11319:10"/> profeſſed the goſpel, many yll diſpoſed perſons began
newe tumultes, and to moue ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea and many ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in
armour. Some of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> realme would haue the goſpel ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly preached. Some other,
would haue that doctrine as newe, and hurtfull, to be condemned and
aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſort, deſyrous of freedom, and quietneſſe,
complayned of their ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry baniſhments, murthers, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and
their moſt miſerable eſtate: wiſhing the ſhame and reproche,
wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with there by they were ſtayned at laſte to be purged. The others
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe, wiſhe their puniſhmentes double, the ſharpeneſſe of
theſame encreaſed, and all their goods committed to fyre and ſweard. And,
to proue their good wyll by their dedes, they brake into their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they could, they robbed their howſen, and finally exerciſed all kynde
of cruelty towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which vnlawful &amp; vnbrydeled luſt, when thoſe
that profeſſed the Ghoſpel, perceiued<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they did more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly prepare to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande them. And many
tymes, wyth armed force reſiſted their inuaſyons. <pb facs="tcp:11319:10"/> And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
greater deceites they vnderſtode were layed for them, the greater trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
and perſecutions that they felt: the greater alwayes grew their courages,
thinking that they ought to withſtande the furious rage of their enemies,
with patience, and ſtoute ſufferaunce. They all agreed it beſt, to
abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> force. But neuettheleſſe, they meant to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde, that
their feare &amp; patience, ſhould not encreaſe the furye and inſolence
of their foes. Firſt of al therfore, wheras, their number was ſo great,
that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation could not aſſemble wythin their priuate howſen:
they determined to come together openly, and to haue their ſermons and
readinges in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen congregations. Partly, bicauſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie
enforced them therto, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cleare themſelues of ſuch
ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous reports as already, their impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aduerſaries had rayſed of
them. For it was openly bruted, that moſt haynous and deteſtable crimes,
were committed in their aſſemblies. Therefore, they came into the yardes
and open places: ſome in their priuate howſen, and ſome in the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
cities. Few toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches. <pb facs="tcp:11319:11"/> For, leaſt any thing ſhould be
raſhly or vnaduiſedly done, or leaſr their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes myght haue any
couloure, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of rebellion: the miniſters &amp; paſtours of
euery Churche (as much as they myght) kept the multitude in awe and order yet
neuertheleſſe, hereof roſe ſondry tumultes, and facrions of their
aduerſaryes. Which notwithſtanding could not ſtaye or hynder their open
metinges. Hereof roſe ſondry troubles and great ſuſpition, and feare of
rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. And, thys cauſed at the laſt, that by the commaundement of the
kyng and hys councell, it was openly proclaimed that none ſhuld iniury or
moleſt other, for any matter of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. After thys al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was publiſhed
an other, whereby, as wel the Biſhops, as other nobles of the realme, were
commaunded to repayre to Poyſſye, to deliberate, both for the leauyeng of a
tribute, to diſcharge the kynges dettes to foren Princes, but chefely for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
reforming of the eſtate of religion. Therby alſo, the kinges peace and
ſafecondwite was graunted to all ſuche as woulde come thither, freely to
propoſe, whatſoeuer perteined to true <pb facs="tcp:11319:11"/> religion; and the
eſtabliſhing of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord. And it was commaunded vnder payne of death, that
no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould trouble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming together, aſſembled, or depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but
that quietly, and freely, they myght mete together, without trouble or
veracion. Shortly after, by an Act of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the Biſhops
and other nobles of the realme, wer not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parties, but rulers: it was
decreed vnder paine of death, that hereafter, none ſhould make any
aſſemblies, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for preaching, or for miniſtring of the Sacramentes,
or for mariage: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where, than in the Churches, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any other
ſorte, than the olde and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed maner. And furthermore, that wythin a
certayne ſpace, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that profeſſed the Ghoſpell, ſhould
departe the realme of Fraunce. Hereof roſe gret trouble. Bicauſe now their
liberty of comming together take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, it was likely, to be greatly
preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the tryall of the whole matter. After thys the nobles met at
Poyſſye. Shortly after, the miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, came to the court
to the king, which then lay at Saynt Germans, nye to <pb facs="tcp:11319:12"/> Poyſſye.
Thither ſomwhat afore; were come certayne choſen men, ſent by the
refourmed churches, out of the .xii. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, to aduaunce religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberating with the others, determined to offer vp to the king, a boke, in
maner of a ſupplication, wherby they woulde uponſome meanes, to
diſputation and conference. Therewithal alſo, was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp, the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of that faith, which they profeſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ready to
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, and defende. Of that boke, the thiefe poyntes were fowre.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that no Biſhops, nor others of the eccleſiaſticall
orders, ſhould vſurpe the authoriti of Iudges ouer vs. Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it
behoueth rather, that they themſelues ſhoulde pleade their owne cauſe,
and ſtande in triall of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the king, Queene, and nobilitie, ſhould rule the
whole do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges: leaſte any trouble might arſie. So that, without contention
and ſtrif, all matters myght be handeled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that al controuerſies might be tryed by the worde of
god: whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:12"/> onely, all our fayth and religion ought to be
grounded.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that certayne notaryes and Scribes, ſhould be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of eyther part which might faithfully regiſter, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wer done or
decreed. Whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhould be of no credite, vnleſſe they were
allowed, and confeſſed of either part. Theſe requeſtes no man
miſliked And the kyng anſwered, that he would take thaduiſe of his
councell, and by his Chauncelour ſhortly make them an anſwere: yet
theſame was long defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Bicauſe the matter was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the
Biſhops, without whoſe councel, or knowledge to do any thing, it ſemed
not mete. For, not only for thys matter of religion, had the kyng aſſembled
them, but alſo, for the leauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of mony, to diſcharge hys dettes. They
waxing proude wyth thys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence, that the kyng ſemed to nede their aide:
aſſured themſelues, of the obtayning of any thyng agaynſte vs, nothyng
doutyng the aſſured conqueſt of Ladye money. Furthermore, they tryfled
and prolonged the tyme, <pb facs="tcp:11319:13"/> ſeeking al occaſions, to auoide our
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and diſputation. For they ſayd we were already condemned and
that they might not diſpute with heretykes. Theſe, and ſuch other like,
their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med ſtayes, they began to blaſe, whiche neuertheleſſe,
afterwardes they denied. Boaſting, that they wer ready to he are vs. For they
were aſhamed openly to refuſe our conference, ſith by their own
conſent, we were ſent for thither. But they fully perſwaded themſelues,
that our courage, or conſtancy would not be ſuch, as to haſard our lyues,
for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeach of our wordes. Duryng this tyme oure nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber increaſed. For
out of euery pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, not in Fraunce onely, but alſo, from al the realmes
adioyning, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as might, without the hynderaunce of their churches, drew
thither. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt we choſe certayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of .xii.
whoſe names wer theſe. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine Malorat, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of Paulon, Iohn
Remonde Merlin, Iohn Mallet, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces Morel, Nicolas Tolye, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Beza,
Claudius Beſſierus, Iohn Bodwine, Iohn Virell. Iohn a Tures. Nicolas
Gallaſius. To theſe, Iohn So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma <pb facs="tcp:11319:13"/> adioyned himſelf, which
openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced papacy, and ſubſcribed to the doctrine &amp; Diſcipline
of our Churches. Afterwardes came alſo, the reuerende father in God, Peter
Martir, ſent for from Tigur. Whoſe comming was ſcarſely acceptable to
our aduerſaryes, aſwell for his ſingular learning, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the
maieſty, and authority, which both his Godlineſſe, and reuerende age haue
gotten hym.</p>
            <p>What in thys meane tyme, was don of the Biſhops, whiche were
aſſembled at Poyſſye, I thynke not good to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. For, leaſt
any man ſhould thynke they were ydle, I wyl ſhew wyth what grauer matters
they were letted, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they could not preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly heare vs. Theſe
queſtions they diſputed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>What ought to be preſcribed vnto Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dignities of
cathedral chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Of the Canonicalls, &amp; their exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions. Of Curates,
&amp; their inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either by preſentation, or ordinary col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Of
aſſigning them a Canonicall portion. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſer (that is to wyt) the
ignoraunt chaplens, and their vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <pb facs="tcp:11319:14"/> number. Of the
reformation of monaſteryes. What ſhould be done of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendes. Of the number
of benefices, and their incompatibility. What waye hereafter they myght
prouide, for chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Monaſteryes in time of vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whether, there
myght be any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, for ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tronerſies as dayly ryſe of
benefyces? Of the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; cenſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche and ſuch
lyke. With y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hard &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty queſtions, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhops occupyed,
had ſo litle leaſure, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they could ſcarſe findeany tyme, to employ in
the hearyng of vs. What meanes they ſought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time to preiudice our
matter, it is not to the purpoſe here to tel, I wil ſhew onely this one.
Which ſome thought in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prologe, or preamble, of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
ſhould enſue: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hereby me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may know, what credite they ought to geue to
ſuch rumors as our aduerſariesfalſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpred vpon vs. For, immediatly
vpon the departure of Theodore Beza, a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure ranne, that he being conuycted
by the Cardinall of Lorayne, was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Catholikes (as they cal
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) and agreed with them, as cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <pb facs="tcp:11319:14"/> the Sacrament
(as they terme it) of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter. Of thys tale, what was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couloure and
occaſion? I wyll ſhortly ſhew. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Beza, the day after hys co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, came
to the Queenes preſence, in the palayce of the kyng of Nauarre, by whom he
was ſent for, there beeyng preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the Prince of Conde, the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of
Borbon &amp; diuers other, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Lorayne emonges others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
there, began to entreate and exhort him, to encline to peace and concorde,
ſaying, that as being abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he had trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the kyngdom, ſo now being
preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he might wel appeaſe it. Hereto, Beza, firſt ſhewing, what good
wil he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes borne, to the kyng and hys na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrey: aunſwered,
that he was not of power, to trouble ſo great a king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome but muche leſſe
of purpoſe to do it, whiche mighte well appeare by hys wrytinges, hopyng
alſo, that they ſhould perceyue greater proofe therof, in hys talke. Then
the Queene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of hys wrytynges. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppon, the Cardenall takynge
oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon, ſayd that he hadde a booke, publyſhed in the name of Beza, in
the <pb facs="tcp:11319:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> which he red one horrible inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Namely,
that Chriſt, is now ſo to be lought in his Supper, as afore he tooke vpon
hym our fleſh, and was borne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin. I haue heard alſo, (quoth he)
that you wrote in a certaine booke, that Chriſt, is in ſuch ſort in his
Supper, as he is in a dunghil. With theſe ſayings, al thoſe that were
preſent were greatly offended. But Beza ſayd. As for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, if they
were preſent, I myght more certainly aunſwere, whether they were myne or
no. But as to the firſt ſentence it may wel ſeeme vnreaſonable as it is
rehearſed of my Lorde Cardinal. But well vnderſtode, and thoſe thinges
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which go afore it, and folowe it, we ſhal fynde it moſt
true. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt is not onely ſhamefull, but wycked alſo, and
blaſphemous. And (I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) can neyther be founde in my
wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, nor any others of our part. Ouer paſſing therfore this laſt,
(in the which, whoſoeuer was the author of it, he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to playne and
manifeſt a lie,) the Cardinall returned to the firſt. It were very hard
(quod he) that we ſhould haue no more than thoſe olde fathers.
Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, <pb facs="tcp:11319:15"/> how could Chriſtes fleſhe be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, afore it
was? Then Beza aſked of the Cardinall, whether from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the
world, there had ben any Church? he graunted. Alſo, was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
Churche, a Church by him, which is the Mediatour betwixt God and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? There to
he agreed alſo. Is not Chriſt, the true God and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theſame Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour?
He confeſſed that alſo. Then (quod Beza) the communicating of the
fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with Chriſt, is not to be limited to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme, in the which in
dede, he ioined his diuinity to our nature. For, that which was not as yet, by
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of nature, was alwayes by power and effect pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the eyes
of our fayth. Is it not ſayd, that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw the day of Chriſt, and
reioyced? Alſo Paule ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our fathers, did eate the ſelfe ſame
ſpiritual foode, and dronke the ſelfe ſame ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drynke, out of
the ſpirituall rocke which folowed them, which rocke was Chriſt. Hereunto
the Cardinall agreed alſo and adioyned here to that which is written in the
Apocalips, that the lamb was ſlayne from the beginning of the world. Then
Beza entreated ſomwhat <pb facs="tcp:11319:16"/> of the difference of the olde and newe
Teſtament. From thys queſtion (as it haps many tymes) they fel into the
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, of the preſence of the body of Chriſt in his ſupper. We do
not agree (quoth the Cardinal) in the expoſition of theſe wordes of our
Lord. This is my body. I graunt (quoth Beza) and I am ſory, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we agree no
better. But I had rather plainly to graunt it, than to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble it. I
(quoth the Cardinall) doe teache the children of my dioceſſe, when they are
aſked, what is the bread of the body of our Lord, to anſwere that it is the
body of Chriſt. Do ye diſalow that? No (quoth Beza). For it is the
ſayinge of Chriſt. But, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion is, after what ſort, the bread is
called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt. For, of thoſe thinges, which are ſayd to be,
all are not ſayd to be after one ſelfe ſame ſort. And there with, he
touched ſomewhat of the Sacramental maners of ſpeaking. Wherin the Cardinal
did not much repugne againſt the ſayings of Beza, onely againſt that
place (but the rocke is Chriſt) whiche Beza cyted, he ſet this. The worde
was made fleſh. But he was ſone made to leaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hold. <pb facs="tcp:11319:16"/> For
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of a natural and eſſential co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, far differeth
from the Sacramental ſpeach. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (quoth Beza)
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in foure pointes. The firſt, is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ſignifyed. The third, of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. The fourth, of the participation of the ſignes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
thinges ſignified by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt (quoth he) we do not agree, that
in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords Supper, you do appoint onely accidentes in ſtede of the
ſignes. Wheras we continue there, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of bread &amp; wine as both the
nature of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments requires, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth.
Here, the Cardinal inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting hym. Truly (quoth he) I thinke my ſelfe able
enough, to defende tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. But, I thynk, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuines might
well inough haue left out y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Neyther would I, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poynt,
ſhould reſt any diurſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our churches. As to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond poynt,
(quoth Beza), we do not only ſay, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meryte of Chriſtes death &amp;
paſſion is ſignified vnto vs, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes of bread and wyne. But
alſo, the true body, that was crucified for vs, and the true bloud which was
ſhed for vs <pb facs="tcp:11319:17"/> and to be ſhort, that Chriſt himſelf, true
God and man, is ſignified vnto vs, by theſe viſible ſignes, that oure
myndes and vnderſtanding may by fayth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually beholde hym in heauen,
where he now aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, reſteth. And ſo, haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruition of all hys
goods and giftes to lyfe euerlaſtyng. And that, aſſone, and as ſurely,
as we ſee, take, eate &amp; drynke, thoſe corporall and viſible ſignes.
The Cardinall agreed hereto, ſignifying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was glad to vnderſtande it.
For that he had heard afore that we taught other wyſe. As to the thirde
(quoth Beza) we graunt, that there is great difference betwixt common water;
&amp; it wherwith we are waſhed in Baptiſme, betwixt breade and wyne whyche
we vſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and thoſe which we receiue in the Lordes Supper. For the
water in Baptiſme, and bread and wyne in the Lordes Supper, be Sacramentes:
that is to wyt, viſible ſignes and teſtimonies of the body and bloud of
our Lord. But this chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, we do not admit, in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the elementes.
But in thys, that they are ſeuered to an other vſe, farre diſtant from
it, whereto naturally they <pb facs="tcp:11319:17"/> be appoynted. For whereas naturally,
they ſerue, to the nouriſhment of the bodye, when they become Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
they repreſent that, whiche ſpiritually fedeth and refreſheth our
ſoules. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, this ſacramentall chaunge, we attrybute, neither to
the Vertue of the worde, whiche any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, neither, to his purpoſe
&amp; intention (as they terme it) but to the power and vertue of god. Whoſe
wil &amp; ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is declared to vs by his worde. In that reſpect
therefore, that the thinge ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, is offered and geuen vnto vs of the
lord, and that, as trulye, as the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof are geuen vnto vs, in that
reſpect, and no other, we acknowledge the coniunction of the ſignes, which
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thinge ſignified. And ſo alſo we ſaye, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and bloud of
Ieſus Chriſt, in that they are truly geuen vs, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated vnto vs, to
be trulye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent alſo, in the vſe of his ſupper, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet is it
therfore to be ſayde, that that body, is ether vnder the bread, or in the
bread, or with the bread, or in any other place, than in heauen, to the whiche
Chriſt aſcended. Wher accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <pb facs="tcp:11319:18"/> to his humane nature he
remaineth till he ſhal come to iudge the quick and the dead. Then the
Cardinall, once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne affirmynge, that he forced not Tranſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
ſayde: that Chriſt in deede, was to be ſought in heauen. Neuertheles he
mixed therwith, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the locall preſence of Chriſte &amp; the
opinyon of certayn Germans ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And ſo confounded theſe matters
together, that it well appeared, he had not bin muche occupied in that article.
Which, he him ſelfe witneſſed alſo, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that he had ſpente the
moſt part of his tyme, in other buſineſſe. I graunt ye (quoth Beza)
that we agre not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> certayne of the Germans, in this third article. But in
this one thing, the grace of god is fauorable to vs al a like, that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on
conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we condemne. Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciation, and whatſoeuer dependeth
thereupon. And all alyke graunt and confeſſe, the liuely communicating, of
the body and bloude of Chriſt. Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ye then (quoth the Cardinall) that we
in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper, do truely, and ſubſtanciallye Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, with the body
&amp; bloude of Ieſus Chriſt? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> remainth (quoth Beza) <pb facs="tcp:11319:18"/> For
the fourth poynte: We do ſaye in effect. That the viſible ſygnes, which
naturally are eaten and dronken, are touched with our ſences, but the thing
ſignified, namely, the body and bloud of Chriſt, truely, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any
coloure or deceit, is offered to al men, but can not otherwyſe be receiued
but ſpiritually, &amp; by fayth. For, thei be not receiued, with one hande or
mouth. Yet neuertheleſſe, thys communicating is ſo certayn, that it,
which we ſee wyth our eyes, &amp; touche with our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no ſurer.
Although the miſery of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of the holy
ghoſt, nether ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſence be perceiued, nor by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of oure
wit comprehended. The Cardinall affirmed that he was ſatyſfied wyth theſe
reaſons. And that openly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed to the Queene. Geuing good hope that
there ſhoulde enſue ſome happye ende of thys conference. He entreated
alſo, and deſyred Beza, that he would oftener talke and conferre with him,
of theſe matters, that ſo at laſt, they myghte make ſome waye to peace
and concorde. So, thoſe that heard thereof, were in greate hope, of
<pb facs="tcp:11319:19"/> better ſucceſſe. But therewithall, ſome came to the
Cardinall, willing hym to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in hys firſt purpoſe, eaſely
ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which afterwards happened. For, the next day, there was a
rumour ſpred, not only in the court, but alſo in Poyſſye, yea and
afterwardes, caryed into farre countreyes, that at the fyrſte meting, Beza
was ouercome, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Cardinals labour. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that
we had now taken the foyle. Theſe, and diuers ſuche other tales, (as
cuſtome is,) were forged &amp; ſpred abrode, which, although they might be
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed with the witneſſe of many credible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet now at laſt,
in tyme prouing themſelues lyes, to their great ſhame, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſt fayned
them, are vaniſhed awaye. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the tyme was thus prolonged and no anſwer
made vnto vs, we came to the nobles of the realm, and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſyred
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we myght be heard: Leaſt in ouerpaſting ſo mete an
occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thoſe, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were ſent, mighte ſeme to ſuſtayne any
ſhame or reproch. But chiefely we required, that thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which
we firſt propoſed, might be obſerued, and that we myght not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:11319:19"/> couple w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our aduerſaries. But chefely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might not be
their owne iudges in the matter. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whatſoeuer ſhuld happen, might
hereafter appeare more certain, we required an anſwere in writing. Which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
it was denied vnto vs, we came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queene, deſiring and beſeching her,
to graunt to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes. There wer preſent, the king of Nauarre, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
prince of Conde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admiral, the Chancelour. The Queene anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Biſhops ſhuld in no wiſe be our iudges. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſuch thigs as wer
done, one of the kinges ſecretaries, ſhuld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter (which was one of
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we call ſecrytaryes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements.) And if we would our
ſelues pen our diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, we might lawfully doe it. And whereas in
decreeing of doctrines we would grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Scriptures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly proteſte. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyng, which had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vs into hys tuycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would be preſent at it, with the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobility.
But ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, to do al thyngs moderatly and wiſely, reſpecting
onely the glory of God, of the aduauncement wherof, ſhe thought vs
deſyrous. But that theſe <pb facs="tcp:11319:20"/> thinges ſhould be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs in
wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, ſhe thougth it was not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente for many cauſes.
Neuertheleſſe, ſhe promiſed we ſhoulde haue it, if we had nede
thereof. Willing vs to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite no leſſe her worde tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her writing.
Foraſmuche as, if ſhe meante to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, her writing could not let her.
Immediatly after our departure, came the doctours of the Sorboniſtes,
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Quene, that ſhe woulde not vouchſafe to heare vs. But if
ſhe were determined to heare vs, at the leaſt, that ſhe ſhould not
ſuffer the kyng to be preſent therat. For that, it was great perill (as
they ſayd) leaſt the king in this his tender age, ſhoulde be
ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned wyth vnſounde doctrine, from the which afterwardes he ſhould
hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be withdrawen. And that we, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuchas we were already condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
of hereſye, were not to be heard at all. Then the Queene aunſwered, that
ſhe woulde doe nothing withoute her councell. Whereby they well perceiued,
that the matter was not likely to paſſe, as they wiſhed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, thoughe all oure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundes <pb facs="tcp:11319:20"/> were not
graunted, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, bicauſe the aunſwere of the Queene, was
tollerable, we thoughte it good, to take the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſte we myghte
ſeeme to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte the conference. The next day therefore whiche was the
nynth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tember, we came to Poyſſye, to the cloyſter of Nunnes, where
the king was, with his brother the Duke of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaunce, the Quene, the king
&amp; Queene of Nauarre, and the reſt of the nobles, with the whole councel,
there were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent alſo, the Cardinalls, and Biſhops, accompaynyed with
a great number of eccleſiaſt call perſons. We miniſters, to the number
of xii. and .xx. of thoſe, whom other churches had ſente, came in afore
them. But, leaſt the people of the towne ſhoulde make any riot vpon vs, the
kinges garde brought vs from our lodginges to the Nunnery. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as we
came to the kinges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and wer commaunded to ſpeake, Theodore Beza,
(which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent was appoynted therto) made an oratyon: in
the which, thankyng God and the Kynge, that nowe at the <pb facs="tcp:11319:21"/> laſt,
our cauſe ſhuld he heard, he ſhewed the cauſes for the which, we had
bin lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before expelled, and vniuſtly conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. Furthermore, in what
articles, we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with our aduerſaries, in what others, and how we did
differ. And what was the meane, to appeaſe all troubles and reforme religion.
Then in fewe wordes, he ſhewed the doctrine of oure fayth and Sacramentes,
and bryefelye touched the chiefe errours, that haue crept into religion, whiche
whyles he handeled grauely moderatly, and wyth ſynguler eloquence, he was
heard very diligently of al men, except when, he treated of the preſence of
the body of Chriſt in his ſupper. For, when he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, how, we are made
partakers of hym in hys Supper, and taught the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame to be done, by the power
of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, which conioyneth &amp; knitteth, thinges moſt farre
diſtance in nature: and that Chriſt, could no otherwyſe be receiued, than
by fayth: and that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to deſcende from heauen, that we may
communicate of hys body: and that he is not encloſed in the bread, but
remayneth in heauen, till he ſhall come <pb facs="tcp:11319:21"/> to iudge the world: or
rather that, as to that corporall preſence, he is as far ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the
bread, as the hyeſt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is diſtant from the loweſt earth: theſe
thinges I ſay. Whiles he handeled, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhops bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to
grudge and murmure. Crying that he ſpake ſhameful blaſphemy. Some
hiſſed, ſome roſe, as though they would depart. And the Cardinall of
Turon ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly deſired, that either he might be licenced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, or we put
to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. They wer ſory that afore they could get no occaſion, to
interrupte our oration. And therfore, it pricked them at the heartes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we
were ſo attentiuely heard. Neither is it to be doubted, but ether they would
haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, or els violently haue runn vpon vs, vnleſſe the very
preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the king, had repreſt their fury. Silence
commaunded a new, Beza, gently deſired them, that they woulde quietly heare
what remained. So it myghte happen, that the matter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they themſelues
mighte be ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So he had licence to conclude. And not onely to
declare the reſydue of thoſe thinges, that pertayne to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb facs="tcp:11319:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> declaratyon of Chryſtes preſence in his ſupper: but
alſo all ſuch thinges, as concerne the Eccleſiaſticall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyne,
and the dutye and authoritye of officers. This oratyon ended, the Cardinall of
Turon perced with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, tremblyng, and freating, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayled the king to
geue no credite to our wordes, nor ſwarue from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of his
aunceſters. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that he mighte obtaine his deſire, he prayed the
gloryous virgine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and the bleſſed Saintes. Then he deſired, to
haue a copy of our orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a daye appointed to aunſwere it. Saying,
that he hoped, that oure argumentes, and reaſons ſhoulde bee ſo fully
ſatiſfied, that if any parte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtucke in the kinges minde, it
ſhoulde thereby, eaſely be rooted oute. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes tooke
aduyſemente with the deuines and Canoniſtes, howe they mighte aunſwere
oure oration. But then the Cardinall of Lorayne, braſte out into theſe
wordes. Would to God, that eyther he had ben dumme, or we deaffe.</p>
            <p>The matter long weyed emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them, <pb facs="tcp:11319:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> they
concluded, not to aunſwere all the poyntes of our oration, (either bicauſe
they would not, or could not) but .ii. on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Firſt, that whiche we ſayde
of the Churche and then that which was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Lordes Supper.
Afterwards they deſired, that they might geue vp a common confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in
wryting, ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by euery of them. Which if the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters would not
allow, they myghte then procede with a ſolemne decree, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And
ſo take away the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. From the whych polecy, the wyſeſt, and
graueſt men abhorring, ſharpely withſtode their purpoſe. In the meane
tyme, we determined, to make ſupplication to the kyng, that he woulde not
ſuffer the conference thus to be broken of, nor the Biſhops to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
in their own cauſe. Saying, that we had not yet ſhewed, the proofes of oure
opynion, but onely ſymplye and playnly, hadde drawen the articles of oure
fayth which afterwardes, myght bee more largely handeled, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the
teſtimonies of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if he did ſuffer the Biſhops, to proocede
ſo at theyr owne wyll <pb facs="tcp:11319:23"/> and decree their own cauſe, it woulde
come to paſſe, that both he ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, of hys good expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
and alſo no remedy hereafter founde for ſuche troubles as do dayly growe.
This ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication was geuen to the Chancelor, who by his prudence, prouided,
that the conference was not broken of, and that the Biſhops kept, farre more
moderate and quiet order than they had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The eight day after, which was the xvi. of theſame moneth, the
Cardinal of Loraine anſwered our oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting afore, that he,
and his, would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſubmit themſelues, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges rule, and would be
ready, to obeye hys commaundement in al pointes: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe,
reſerued place, for theyr wonted immunitie and fredom, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, they are wont
to quite themſelues from all ſubiection, and chalenge the chiefe
authoritie. And that he did ſo ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telly, that he ſcarcely ſemed, to
touche that ſore. And pretending a coloure of concorde, he proteſted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
he would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue vs, which had ſwarued from him, if we would returne,
&amp; humble our <pb facs="tcp:11319:23"/> ſelues to them. To conclude that they would
be, as fathers towards vs. If we would ſhew our ſelues, as children
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them. Theſe, &amp; ſuch other like, afore promiſed, he ſayd
he would aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere onely to the Articles of our orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whereof the one
concerned the Church, the other the Lordes Supper. He ymagined, that we had
ſo defyned y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Church, as though, the name thereof, had extended no farther,
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the elect: and therfore largely reaſoned agaynſte it, ſhewing out
of the common ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the goſpel, (in the whiche, it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,
to a plat of grounde, and to a fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers net,) that the name therof, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
euen to ill and reprobate perſons. But he gaue it a meruaylous definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
Saying, that the Catholike Church is it, which is euery where knowen, and of
all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To the authority of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church, he ſayd, al interpretation of
Scriptures and making of traditions ought to bee referred. Saying that the
ſucceſſion, as well of that Church, as of the paſtours therof, was
perpetual but of the Lordes Supper, he ſo entreated, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> touching no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at
al, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natures of <pb facs="tcp:11319:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> the elements, he came
very nye to their opinion, which ioyne the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, with
the elementes. And ſay, that they be both vnder them, and in them. Which
afterwardes, we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode, was done for a polecy, partly, to procure their
fauoure, whom he had ſo kindly clawed, and partly, to make vs the more
hatefull to them. Neither yet did he plainly agree with them, but ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
that in thys reſpect, he did willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioyne with them, that they myghte
ioyntly warre againſt vs. The ende of his oration, was to this effect. That
the kyng and his counſell, leauing our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſhould folow the ſteppes
of theyr for fathers, and not leaue their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vſage. When he had
ended, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that preſently, whiles the memory therof was yet
freſh, we might ſatiſfye his obiections, and refute his argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. For
we feared, leaſt after thys the Cardinals anſwere, we ſhould ſcarcely
haue leaſure or liberty afterwardes to ſpeake. Bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day afore,
many brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld loke for nothing els, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> condemnation, &amp;
the thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derbolt of exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication. Neyther wer we ignorant <pb facs="tcp:11319:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> therof. The Queene, taking the aduiſe of her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs
to depart, ſaying: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould anſwere it an other tyme, &amp; that
ſhe would appoint vs a day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t again. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
meruaile had it ben, if the byſhops, which wer of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, would haue
geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other councel. The next day againe we deſired y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might be
preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly heard and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme no longer prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged. But we could obtayne
nothing, neither wer we heard, before the eight day. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time, falſe
rumors were ſpred abrode, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wer ouercome, &amp; put to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp;
had nothyng to ſay. Whereas we were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to haue anſwered their oration
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. And how falſe ſuch tales be, here by men may ſufficiently
geſſe, that the Biſhops did what they could, to breake of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference,
ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the laſt, by their importunity they obteined of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queene that
the matter ſhuld not be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly heard afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, but in a more ſecret
place, afore few. Therfore, it was deferred, til the .xxiiii. day of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moneth
at the whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to returne to Poyſſye, we came before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quene,
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king &amp; Queen of Nauarre, &amp; the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes and
<pb facs="tcp:11319:25"/> counſallours, there were preſent alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. Cardinalles, and
many Byſhops, and diuynes of al ſortes: we the myniſters, were admitted
only to the number of xij. Thoſe being ſeuered which wer ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other
Churches, which afore were ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs. For now the matter was heard, both in
narower place, &amp; in leſſe companye than before, the Cardynals of
lorayne ſhewed in few wordes, that this aſſemblye was to this end, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if
we would obiecte any thing, agaynſt that which he had ſayde eyght dayes
before, we might freely ſpeake, &amp; ſhuld be herd. Then Beza, in the name
of vs al, ſaid: That he would haue wiſhed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atlye he might haue
aunſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynalls oration, whyles the ſame was freſh in memorye
or at the leaſt, that he might haue had ſom copye therof, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might,
au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere certaynly &amp; perfectly to euery poynt, but, foraſmuch as he
coulde not obtayne that, he woulde aunſwere ſo much as he coulde call to
mynde. Fyrſte there fore, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the article of the Churche, which
the Cardinall fyrſte handled, he deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it into thre partes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:25"/>Firſt, what it is. Then, what are the marks therof.
Thirdly, what and how great is the authoritie therof. It is wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (quoth
he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this name Eccleſia. (which ſignifieth the church) is deriued from
the Greeke <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifyeth to
call fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on place to another. Of calling, we find .ii. ſorts in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſcriptures, the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned with the working of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt: wherof
Paul to the Romains writeth, whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, them he iuſtified.<note place="margin">Rom. viii c. xxviii.</note> The other, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe in outward
ſhew. It be al one with the firſt: yet is altogether vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to
ſaluation. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only through the fault of man, beyng deaffe at the calling
of God. Of this calling, ſpake the Lorde, when he ſayde. That many wer
called but fewe choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Mat. xxii. b. xiiii.</note> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
it happens, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the name of the church (which ſignifyeth the congregacion of
thoſe, that are aſſembled by the word of god) is taken .ii. wayes. For,
generally it contayneth al thoſe, which outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſe to folowe the
calling of god. Neyther is it to be doubted, but manye hypocrites, and
reprobate perſons are within this nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. Neither we thanks <pb facs="tcp:11319:26"/> be
to god therefore) haue at any tyme, Either written or taught otherwiſe, for
aſmuch as, both the ſcripture, and alſo common experience doth plainly
proue the ſame, but, takyng this name of the churche proprely, and
ſtreyghtlye, (as, manye tymes we doe) we then ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it comprehendeth
onlye the electe and choſen of god. And, that al men may know, that we be not
the authours of this maner of ſpeache, or of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, when it is
written, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt, bones of his bones, fleſhe
of his fleſhe, yea, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſt it ſelfe is geuen vnto
it,<note place="margin">Eph. ii g. xxx.</note> (as Paule wrytyng to the
Corinthians, ioyning the members with the heade, calleth her Chriſt)<note place="margin">i. Cor. xii. b. xii. xvii.</note> how could in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be
contayned the reprobate, in as muche as, they are the members of the deuill?
For it cannot bee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde be members bothe of Chriſt and of the
deuil, which Auſtine writyng agaynſte Creſconius, well noteth in his
ſeconde booke, and xxiiii. Chapter. He alſo wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng on the .lxiiii.
pſalme, vſed this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction of the churche, ſaying: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> that church
whiche is ſignifyed by Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:26"/> toke her begynnyng of Abel,
and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, of Eain. And afterwardes in his fyrſt booke of baptyſme,
agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes, the ſeconde Chapter, wheras he taketh, the name
of the church more largely, he ſaieth, that he, that begot A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, Enoch,
Noe, Abraham, &amp; the reſte of the Prophetes, begot alſo Cayn,
Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maell, Dathan, and ſuche lyke. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude, we muſte take
that whiche Auſtine hymſelfe wrote in the ſeuenth boke of the ſame
booke, the. 51. chapter, whiche is alſo rehearſed .xxiiii. ix. i. a. ca.
All thyngs conſydred it is ſaid that there are two kynde of men in the
churche.</p>
            <p>Some of them (ſayeth he) bee the members of Chriſte, and of
the houſe of God, yea the houſe of GOD it ſelf. Other ſome bee in the
houſe, but not of the houſe. For they bee as chaffe with the corne, tyll
ſuche tyme as they bee ſeuered. Hereof ryſeth a queſtyon whether the
Churche bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible? Whiche I thynke good to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme, and to conclude,
that onely God knowes his elect &amp; choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we
beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is a holy church, <pb facs="tcp:11319:27"/> whiche is conceiued, imagined
and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued, not ſeene. For if we ſhuld other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaie, thereof would
enſue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is moſt repugnaunt to reaſon. For if the churche be
vnknowen vnto vs, to what flock ſhal we ſtickto be pertakers of
ſaluation, when to the Church only Chriſt extendeth his power &amp;
ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? we ſay therfore, that althoughe that Churche can not be
diſcerned by ſight, yet when we ſeeke to what flocke and companye we
ought to aſſocyate oure ſelues, ther be certayne notes, wherby we may
know &amp; diſcerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the pure worde of god, and the
ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere adminiſtration of the ſacraments. Theſe be the cleare and
euident marks thereof, neither is there any doute, but whatſoeuer theſe be,
ther is alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Church of god. Furthermore, we ſay: That al thoſe,
that profeſſe true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are charitablye to be counted amonge the
number of the faythful, vnleſſe, the lorde do playnely deteſt their
hipocriſy and deſſemblynge. Whereof, Paule giueth vs a manifeſt
preſident callinge the Corinthians and Galathians faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii. a</note> and applying to them, the general
<pb facs="tcp:11319:27"/> name of the churche, albeit in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was great imperfection,
aſwel of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as life, whiche in diuers places he himſelfe
complaineth. For, all thoſe that haue any foundation, doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies builde
on the ſame, golde, ſiluer, and pretious ſtones onely: but alſo
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, hey, chaffe, and ſedge.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii. c
xii.</note> In this maner and ſort therefore, we vſe to ſpeake of the
church, leaſt we ſhould ſeme to appoint any fantaſticall thing or that
ſhould conſiſte in imaginations onely, or leaſt we mighte geue any
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, to ill diſpoſed perſones, to deeme vs ſuche, as were in times
paſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thares and Donatiſtes, and in this our age are the
Anabaptiſtes, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſoned about this
que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Nowe let vs come to the markes and ſignes of the true churche,
whiche is neceſſary to be diſcerned &amp; knowen, ſith out of her is no
ſaluation. And for that cauſe Sathan, that olde enemye of man, hath
attempted by all meanes poſſible, to diſguiſe and counterfayte her, to
chaunge her auncient ſygnes, and fayne newe in their places. Her vncertaine
and vndoubted markes, we <pb facs="tcp:11319:28"/> haue ſayde to be two, that is to
we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, the pure preachyng of the woorde and adminiſtration of the
ſacramentes. Hereto, doe ſome adioyne eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, and
fruites of fayth. And trulye, it is neceſſary, that euery flock ſhould
haue ſome head and guyde who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they oughte to obey, yf they mynde to liue in
ſafetye: but foraſmuche as oure owne iniquities, often tymes are the
cauſe, that we wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two laſt markes, let vs content our ſelues with
the fyrſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that the worde of god is the certayne ſygne of the
churche, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth, that bothe Chriſte and Peter compare the ſame
to ſeede.<note place="margin">Mat. xiii. a. iii iiii. xi. i. Pet. i. d.</note>
For the whiche cauſe alſo, Paule ſayth, that he begat the Corinthians in
Chriſt, by preachyng the worde.<note place="margin">i. Cor. iiii c. xv.</note>
Therefore in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe places, it is called one foode and nouryſhemente:
this alſo Chriſte hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth to pertayn to his ſhepe,
ſaying: that they heare his voice and no others.<note place="margin">Iohn.
x.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We adioyne hereto the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes alſo, for that Chriſte
woulde not onelye, to oure eares, but alſo to our eyes, and the reſte of
oure bodylye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenſes <pb facs="tcp:11319:28"/> wytneſſe his grace. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
he ordeyned the Sacramentes, to be certain and viſible ſignes, both of oure
vnion with hym, and alſo of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye and loue among oure ſelues. For that
cauſe, duryng the olde Teſtament it was ſayde, that they ſhoulde be
ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed the companye of the faythfull, whiche had not the ſygne of
cyrcumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And furthermore decreed, that all houſeholders ſhoulde
thrice in the yere, appeare before the Lorde, at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, by common
ſacrifyce, to teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye the vnitye of fayth and religion.<note place="margin">Exodus xxxiiii. d. xxiii.</note> Afterwardes, the Vyneyarde beyng
ſpoyled, the Gentyles grewe in one bodye with the Iewes, not onely by
preachyng the woorde, but alſo, by the Sacramentes of Baptyſme, and of the
bodye and bloude of oure Lord. Yea, and Chriſte commaunded his Apoſtles
ſo to dooe, ſaying: goe ye, and teache all nations:<note place="margin">Mat.
xx. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xix.</note> This is the
doctryne of the woorde, to the which he foorthwith adioyneth the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
ſaying: Baptyſing, in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the holy
ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:29"/>For, to baptiſme alſo, muſt we applye that,
which Paule writeth of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſaying: that what he receiued of the
Lorde, he deliuered to vs.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi. c xxxii.</note> And
theſame he teſtifieth in an other place alſo. Namely, that the Churche is
founded vppon the foundation of the prophetes and the Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Ephe. ii. d xx.</note> that is to wete, vpon Ieſus Chriſt, who
is the ſumme &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of all the doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and
Prophetes. So alſo muſt we vnderſtande another texte of the ſame
Apoſtle. Where he ſayeth, that the Churche is a piller of the liuing God, a
bolſter of truthe.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii. d. xv.</note> Whiche
meaneth, that the woorde of God, whiche is the truthe it ſelfe, dothe ſtaye
and vpholde the church, or els is placed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, as in an open and
ſure fortreſſe, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in her god extendeth his power &amp; health to
all beleuers,<note place="margin">Rom. i</note> theſe are the true and
viſible ſignes of the churche. Whiche therefore is called the mother of the
faithfull, for that they wer begotten in her, by incorruptible ſeede, and
noury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and fed with the ſame fode. If the preaching of the woorde, and
the true adminiſtration of the ſacramentes, be <pb facs="tcp:11319:29"/>
neceſſarily required in the churche, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſte there needes be
paſtours &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to execute theſame. As the holye ſcriptures
ſufficientely witneſſe, but chieflye Paule writyng to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians
and Epheſians, this was the cauſe, that this thirde marke was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned
hereto.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xii. d. xxviii. Ephe. iiii vi. xi. i. Timo.
iii. a Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. i. a vi.</note> Namely,
ordinary ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, from the time of the Apoſtles. Hereto we
aunſwer, that ſuch ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is muche to be eſteemed, if it be
wel conſidered, and applied after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the auncient fathers, who
grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereon againſt heretikes, &amp; there newe opinions. As Tertulian,
Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Auſtine againſte the Maniches and Donatiſtes, but becauſe
many lay the ſame againſt vs, as though we had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyed into the churches
new ſciſmes and hereſies, it is neceſſarye, that we ſhould ſhew
our minde herein. We ſay therefore, that there is one ſucceſſion of
doctrine, an other of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Doctrine we graunt to be the true and
vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mark of the churche as it hath bene already ſaide. For, although
the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell, bee not therefore the more to be credited, for
that it is the <pb facs="tcp:11319:30"/> auncienteſt of all other (thoughe it happen many
tymes for oure ſynnes, that theſame ſeeme ſo new &amp; ſtraunge to
menne, as it ought to bee familiar and vſuall) yet neuertheleſſe, the
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the continuall ſucceſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is of no ſmall
force, to wynne it authoritye amonges menne. As to the ſucceſſion of
perſones, we admitte it, but ſo that it be conioyned wyth the
ſucceſſion of the Propheticall and Apoſtolyke doctryne, in
ſubſtance and the chiefe poyntes and groundes at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leaſte. But, we ſpeake
of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne it ſelfe, not of theyr maners. For, albeit, it be required,
of true and faithfull paſtours, that in doctryne and lyfe they be ſounde
and pure, yet for the ignoraunce of ſome thynges, or for the diuerſitie of
opinions in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, ſo that it ſtretch not to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of our
ſaluation, or though ther life be not of the perfecteſt, yet for theſe
thynges we doe not reiect them, but beare them. So they kepe the grounde and
foundation. And that we ought ſo to doe, Chriſt teacheth vs, ſaying: that
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scribes and Phariſes ſitting <pb facs="tcp:11319:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> in Moyſes
chayre teache vs, we oughte to folowe their doctryne, and not their
deedes.<note place="margin">Mat. xxiii a. ii. iii.</note> Whiche place, Auſtine
writing vppon Iohn, ſayeth: ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande of ſuche hyerlyng
paſtours as keepe the ſounde doctrine, but not of falſe Prophetes, of
whom Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywyſe ſayde.<note place="margin">Auguſt. tracta.
xlvi</note> Beware of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the Phariſees.<note place="margin">Mat.
xvi. a. vi. vi. xi</note> Whyle they ſitte (ſayeth Auſtine) in the chayre
of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they teache the lawe of God, and ſo god teacheth by them. But
yf they teache theyr owne doctryne, neyther heare theyr woordes, neyther folowe
their deedes. That alſo the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor expreſſeth more at large, in
hys xlix. Sermon, of the woordes of the Lorde. Foraſmuche as therefore,
falſe Prophetes and wolues maye ſuccede to true and faythfull paſtours,
we dooe not onelye, not admitte perſonall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, but euen
condemne it, vnleſſe the ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of doctrine be ioyned with all,
becauſe it is a meete cloke for anye lye or errour. Furthermore if perſonal
ſucceſſion of it ſelf ſhoulde be taken for a certayn mark of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
church, ther ought to haue ben ſom promis of god ſhewed <pb facs="tcp:11319:31"/>
wherby he hath limited his grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certayn ſea or countrey. Whiche in
the new Teſtament, we ſhal not find. In deede he promiſed, that the
churche ſhoulde be Catholike, that is to were, vniuerſall, whiche is ſo
called, for that the particuler members thereof, are here and there,
diſperſed throughoute the whole worlde. Wherſoeuer it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth god to
ſhewe his iudgementes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he vtterly cutteth of, or
whom he chaſteneth for a tyme, or in ſhewyng mercy to them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he
furthereth better and better, or whom he calleth to his knowledge and
ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For in ſome places, the Lord iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuenging himſelf ſo
deſtroyeth the churche, that he ſeemeth euen to roote it oute, and not to
leaue ſo muche as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſigne therof, as it hapned amonges the barbarous
nations and in the moſt part of all the Eaſte. Otherwhere, as in Greece,
and other realmes more nie to vs, he hath lefte ſome tokens of the churche.
Agayne, ſometyme the Lorde dothe cut and breake of, onely the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall
ſucceſſion of paſtours: as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at Antioche, in the time of
Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatenus, <pb facs="tcp:11319:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> and at Alexandria after the baniſhment
of Athanaſius, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other churches. And, that we neede to ſeeke no
further: the perſonall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, then at the leaſt fayled in the
Romaine churche, when Honorius be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing biſhop, was condemned for the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable hereſie of the Eutichians. And ſo likewiſe in the time of
Iohn, the. xxii of that name, who was alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned for hereſie.
Vnleſſe perhaps ſome man wyll mayntayne, that thoſe that are
manifeſtly condemned of hereſye, be paſtours. Furthermore in what caſe
this ſucceſſion ſtoode vnder Iohn the ſhee Pope, through the
ſciſmes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of diuerſe, ſtriuyng for the Popes ſea, the
hiſtories ſufficientlye witneſſe. Wherfore we conclude, that not
reſpectyng the perſonall ſucceſſion of paſtours, we muſt alwayes
haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to the pureneſſe of doctrine, and the ſincere
adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſo that they onely be to be counted
ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of the Apoſtles, whiche beyng lawfully called, doe buylde
vpon theyr foundation. Whether they deriue their ſucceſſion from them, or
whether the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame <pb facs="tcp:11319:32"/> haue fayled. And contrarywyſe, they that
neyther buylde nor teache, or preache theyr owne doctrine in ſtede of the
Apoſtles, although they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhewe neuer ſo many and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall
preſidentes of their predeceſſors, are not to be taken for paſtours,
but to be ſhu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned as wolues, as Chriſt and his Apoſtles teach. Some manne
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes will obiecte. Is it therfore law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man to teache, and
myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacramentes? no. For it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth (as the Apoſtle ſayeth)
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thinges bee done in the houſe of God, ryghtly, and orderly.<note place="margin">i.
Corint. xiiii. g. xi.</note> Who then ſhall bee taken for true paſtours?
they whiche are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called. It remayneth then, that we vnderſtande,
what is a lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng And here I muſt craue attention. For we ſaye
that ſome callyng is ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narye, and ſome extraordinarye. Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narye is it,
in the whiche is obſerued the order appoynted by GOD in hys churche. In that
order theſe three thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are chiefly requyred.</p>
            <p>Firſte the examination of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and lyfe that ſhalbe
ordayned, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lawfull choyſe and election. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <pb facs="tcp:11319:32"/>
the laying of handes. And theſe we all gathered out of diuers places of the
ſcripture. As oute of the Actes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the writinges of
Paule to Timothe and Titus.<note place="margin">Ac. i. d. xii Ioh. vi. a. vi. i.
Tim. ii. a. ii. et. iii. d. xxii. Titus. i. a. vi</note> This therefore is the
ordinarye callyng. Whereby we may well diſcerne whiche is it, that we call
extraordinarye. Namely it, that wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth ſom one, or other, or al theſe
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and yet the ſame grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the authoritie of God, and
lawfull. That god vſed ſuche extraordinary cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngs, it plainly appeareth
throughout the whole ſcripture. For who laid han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vpon Moyſes, that he
myght conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate Aaron? Who gaue the gyfte of Prophecye, to Eſay, Danyeil,
Amos, and the reſt?<note place="margin">Exodus. xxviii. Eſa. vi. b. xciii.
Dani. i. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vii. Amos. vii
xiiii</note> Yea, was not this geuen them, when they, that ordinarilye had the
charge thereof, abuſed it? For then it was neceſſarye, that god ſhoulde
put to his hande extraordinarilye: not to trouble or confounde the order of hys
churche, but to correcte them, whiche vnder the pretence of ordinary
ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſſordred all. This well proue the writyngs of the
Prophets, which moſt of al pertain to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> orders of the prieſtes.
<pb facs="tcp:11319:33"/>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. xxviii vi. vii. Iere. vii. a. iiii et.
xxiii. a. xi. Ezec. xxii e. xxvi. Soph. iii. a. iiii.</note> But if it be
obiected, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche men gaue ſome certayntye, of their vocation, as either
ſome miracle, or ſome heauenly ſigne: I graunt the ſame to be true in
ſome, but not in all. Neither can any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay otherwiſe, vnleſſe he
wil plainly denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. Neither do Iwel know, whether we ſhall find many
prophetes of the ſtocke of Aaron, or vpon whom, after the ordinary maner,
hands were layde. But yf any man will take this exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thoſe
prophets vſed only to rebuke vice and we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t no farther, but abſtained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſacrifice: I au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that is not true in all. For Samuel, which was not
of the ſtock of Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſacrificed in Miſpa: And Elias of Galaad, in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
mount Carmelus.<note place="margin">i. Samu. vii. c. ix i. Regum xviii. f.
xxvi.</note> Then is it not to be maruelled, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophets of that time
woulde extend theyr office ſo far, as to circumciſe &amp; ſacrifice,
whereas that by enheritaunce appertayned onely to the tribe of Leuy? But
ſuche enheritaunce at this daye hath no place: thus you ſee, what we call
the church, what we think of her markes: and of the callyng of paſtours in
her. Which yf you pleaſe to applye, to oure Churches, or to oure <pb facs="tcp:11319:33"/> ſelues we hope, that by the helpe of god, we ſhall ſhewe ſuch
profe, and witneſſe therof, out of the holy ſcriptures, as no man ſhall
haue any occaſion to doute thereof. And that, both according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of
god, &amp; alſo to the writings of that godly man Auſtyne, at the leaſt
in that treatyſe, which is reckned among his workes, and intitled of. 65.
queſtion the laſt queſtion. Now let vs ſpeake of the authoritye of the
churche. By that, which we haue alreadye ſpoken, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that we
derogate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her none of thoſe hye &amp; precious titles, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy
ghoſt doth geue her, but ſay that ſhe is the bodye of our lorde,
obtayning the ſame here only in part, til ſuch time, as ioyned to her head,
ſhe ſhall fullye and perfectly enioye the ſame.<note place="margin">Heb.
xi. c. xv i. Co. i. a. vii. i Cor. xiiii vi. v. Ep. iiii. c. xv.</note> She is
the houſe of god, but ſuche as is daylye put of and increaſed. She is
ruled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god, but as yet ſhe ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
fleſh.<note place="margin">Gala. v. c. xvii.</note> She is clenſed &amp;
waſhed but ſo, that by litle, and litle, ſhe ſhalbe brought to that
perfect beautye, in the which ther ſhalbe no ſpott, no wrinkle.<note place="margin">Ep. v. f. 25 i Co. 3. c. 4</note> She knowes god but only in part.
And in theſe our maners of ſpeache, we wiſh <pb facs="tcp:11319:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> the
Apoſtles wordes to be weyghed, to conclude, we graunt, that there is no
ſaluation without the church. For ther is no ſaluation but in Chriſt
Ieſus.<note place="margin">i. Ihon. v. c. xi. Iohn. iii. c. xviii.</note> And
Chriſt dothe no where extende his ſaluation, but in thoſe members,
whoſe congregation, and communion is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the churche, but it is doubted,
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe maye erre in this worlde, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we bee ſubiecte to the
ſcripture, or els her authoritie excede theſame. We aunſwere, that her
ſeuerall members maye erre, and dayly fall and fayle, as well in doctrine, as
in lyfe, accordyng to the ſaying of Paule. In parte we knowe.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xiii c. ix.</note> Alſo Iohn ſaieth: If we ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
we haue no ſinne, we deceue our ſelues and there is no truthe in vs.<note place="margin">i. Iohn. i. d. viii.</note> Wherfore if any man will goe aboute,
to excepte the doctours from this number, lette him pardon vs, that we beleue
him not. For we coulde eaſily ſhewe many au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorityes, wherein do appeare
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt errours of the beſt learned, &amp; moſte auncient doctours.
Be it ſpoken wyth their leaue and fauour, whom as well for their ſinguler
learnyng, as alſo for their paſſing pitie, we doe muche reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
Neither truely, my L. Cardinal, <pb facs="tcp:11319:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> (if I wel vnderſtoode
him) doth admy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without iudgement. This therfore is our opinion of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church ſeuerally, whoſe inperfection is not ſo material,
but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For, by litle &amp; litle, they
daily profit &amp; encreaſe, aſwel in amending of their liues, as
encreaſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their learning. But now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> parts of the Churche
more generally, as deuiding it into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral dioceſſes, &amp; prouinces,
ſhal we ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may erre? That they bothe may erre, &amp; alſo haue
erred, my L. Cardinal (if Iwel reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) hath alredy grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great &amp; long experience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no wiſe man
maie wel doubt therof. It remaineth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conſider the whole &amp;
vnyuerſall churche. But firſt we muſt ſee in what ſort. For if we
conſider it, as it is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by ſom general counſel,
aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we muſt not thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt
exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church, is reſtrained to any certain nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
which ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times, are neither the beſt learned, nor beſt liuers. For howe
oft hapneth it, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſome one priuate man, paſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt lerned, yea
&amp; ſomtimes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> whole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel in wit &amp;
knowledge? For this cauſe, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince it hath bine writen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better
credyte is to be geuen, to any pryuate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding a better reaſon, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
either to any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celor or pope.<note place="margin">glo. in. ca.
ſignificaſti de .elect. i ibi. pauo</note> And hereof their is a notable
example in the councell of nyce. For what ſtayed, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prohibition of
mariage. Which hath bred ſo much filthynes in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church, had not then bine
ſtabliſhed &amp; decreed? only paphumtius as the hiſtory recordes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
ſtode it. Or what conuocation of any generall councel hitherto hath bene ſo
larg, but that a greate number of holye and learned men, yea &amp; of the
worthyeſt biſhops, hath bene ouerpaſſed therin? And who will affirme
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothing more is reueled to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are abſente, than to thoſe that
are preſent at the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell? Furthermore you are not ignorante, what horrible
confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther hath bene, and is at this preſent in the church, and chiefly
amonges thoſe that ſitt in hyeſt comes. So that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of god, euen
there wher it ſhould be moſt pure and perfect, doth appeare moſt
confuſe and deſolate. And long time hath this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched caſe continued,
there yet remaine <pb facs="tcp:11319:35"/> ſo many greuous &amp; leude complaintes of
good biſhops, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſemeth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now
preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli to pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yne eares. What in his time, Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a had wrote in his
bokes, de conſideratione et ſermone, 33 ch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vppon the Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a
Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>corum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alſo in hys ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Paul, it is no
leſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, than true. Alas, alas, o lord god, they are chefe in
perſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which ſeme
to be chefeſt in thy church, &amp; to beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt rule therein. They
haue take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtell of Sion: they haue wonne y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nicions, &amp; now
frely, &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyer the whole citye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Theſe things we ſpeake not in reproch of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to ſhew, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for as
much as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chef calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded, &amp; gone aſtray, it
can not be proued, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, (which haue bin
aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled many times, of a multitude of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt vnfit therfore,) are
ſo guided w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grace of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holi goſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may not erre. The old
prieſt (of whom I would make no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> his example is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly
aledged for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profe hereof) although he were vitious &amp; wicked, did
prophe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was neceſſari y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld <pb facs="tcp:11319:36"/> die for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> people, leaſt the whole nation ſhuld periſh. But
neuertheleſſe, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, or counſell is not therfore alowed, as though
he had rightfullye conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned Chriſt. For the holy goſt prophecied it, &amp;
not he, which vnderſtode not what he ſpake. For he was ſtyrred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſpirit, and altogether deuilliſhe For he gaue iudgement againſt
the innocent Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſon of god. Furthermore, if this priuilege be
geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cannot erre, either in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rule of
doctrine, or forme of life, we woulde fain know, at what time this was done For
there was alwaies one faith, &amp; one church.<note place="margin">Ephe. iiii a.
v</note> In the olde churche &amp; vnder the olde teſtamont the hiſtories
&amp; prophets witneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> errours were commonlye taught &amp; receiued.
All their ſpies (ſaith Eſay) be blind, their dogges bee du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, not able
to barke.<note place="margin">Pſa. lvi. d x.</note> Alſo Ieremy: Bothe
prophete &amp; prieſt, do all forge lyes<note place="margin">Iere. vi.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xv.</note> And leaſt you
ſhould thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liues of priuate perſons it
in writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame prophet: the prophetes prophecy falſly in my
name.<note place="margin">Ier. xiiii. c. xiiii.</note> For I ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not,
neither did I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund them to ſpeak, neither did I ſpeak vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but
<pb facs="tcp:11319:36"/> lying viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, diuinations, yea nothyng, or y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s of
their own hert, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie vnto you. Alſo Eſai: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſdom of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
wiſe ſhal periſh, &amp; the witte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> witty ſhal hide it
ſelfe.<note place="margin">Pſ. xxiiii. c. xiiii.</note> Alſo Ezechiell: The
law ſhal periſh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt, &amp; councel from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elders.<note place="margin">Ezec. vii. g. xcvi.</note> Furthermore, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
prophets, as Ieremy, Michae, yea &amp; the ſon of god himſelf, &amp; his
Apoſtles, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> councels of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes of Iſrael? If any man
anſwer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe things hapned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we will
replie, that he doth not ſatiſfy our reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor ſpeake any thing to
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purpoſe. For not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion remaineth That y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
cau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ls of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prelates, albeit they wer v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal, wer ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times ruled
rather w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſpirit of error tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god. But that we may com to the newe
teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, did not Paul ſpecially warne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church, writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Epheſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wolues ſhould com fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Acte.
xx. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xix.</note> &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſon of perdition ſhuld ſit in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god?<note place="margin">ii.
Theſſa ii. a. iiii.</note> And truely yf we weigh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels
ſeuerallye, we ſhal find ſo much repugnant &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariety in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
we muſt nedes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holye goſt ruled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, but Sathan,
whiche long ſince knowes how to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſform hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <pb facs="tcp:11319:37"/> into an
Angell of light. There is a place very manifeſt in Auſtine, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
this, in hys ſeconde booke of Baptiſme againſt the Donatiſtes, the
thirde Chapter, wherein he plainly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the writinges of ſeueral
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, are amended by particuler coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. And prouiniciall Synodes by
vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall. And vniuerſall counſels refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by others after, when by
experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that is detected, which afore was hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or that diſcloſed,
which afore was coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Where Auſtyne doth not entreate of the outwarde
forme, but of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, and of the Aphricane councell, wherin thei did
deliberate, whether thei ought to be Baptiſed againe, that had bin Baptiſed
of hereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es. There wyll perhaps be obiected an other reaſon, commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough,
namely, that Chriſte did promiſe, as oft as .ii. or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
together in his name, to be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the middeſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">Math. vi, viii. c. xx.</note> And therefore much
more he would be preſent at a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral councel. We grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ye, that may wel be
preſumed, but farr differs a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption from a neceſſary
concluſion. For, ſuch is the naughtineſſe of men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:37"/>
they abuſe the name of God, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing of their own lyes. And they
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes haue the name of God moſte in their mouthes, whoſe heartes ar
ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies and haters of God.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv. c. ix.</note> And
whereas the weakeneſſe of mannes witt is ſuch, as dayly experience
proueth, and many are blynded with noughty affections: We ſay that thoſe
that grounde on no other foundation, than the iudgemente of men, and coloure of
a councell, are in great perill. How then? Thynk we that the doctrine of the
Church is vncertam for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe may erre? No. For we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that although we
knowe God onely in parte as Paule ſayeth, and in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, error is
mingled with the truthe, yet God did neuer permit, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe, and
ſubſtantiall poyntes were wholye ouerthrowen and buryed. For alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s he
hath reſerued to hymſelfe a flocke, ſome tymes greater, &amp; ſometymes
leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, to ſpeake and vnderſtande thoſe thynges, which it behoueth,
both to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande &amp; ſpeake. As in Elias tyme in Iſraell. Alſo in
the captiuity of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and about the comming of Chriſt. At which tyme,
ſcarſe Zacharias onely, <pb facs="tcp:11319:38"/> Elizabeth, Ioſeph, the virgine
Marye, Simon, and Anne the Propheteſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, that knew God: and among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
ſo great corruption of the Scribes and Phariſes, did truely vnderſtande
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Prophecies. Suthe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches whiche happen in the churche
of God for our ſinnes, be as it were tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes, whiche afterwardes the
Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> calmes, and lyke cloudes, which vaniſh awaye at the riſing of the
ſonne. Dooe we then condemne the olde councels? God forbidde. For if by theyr
decrees thinges ſhoulde bee refourmed, you knowe that you ſhould be
compelled to chaunge more than we. Onely this we deſire, that the ſcripture
maye be to vs as a toucheſtone, whereby all thinges ought to be allowed, that
are doone or ſpoken in the churche. Whiche yf anye man thinke vnreaſonable,
let him read that famous ſaying of Auſtine, writing to Maximinus the Arian
in his ſecond booke and .xiiii. chapter, where he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel
of Nice and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum. For I thinke there is no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, that maye rather bee
called vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, than the firſt councel of Nyce. <pb facs="tcp:11319:38"/> And
contrariwyſe, all menne confeſſe, that the councel of Ariminum, oughte
worthily to bee reiected and condened. Vppon what occaſion dothe Auſtine
talke of thoſe two councels? About the controuerſie of an article of our
fayth, nowe confirmed &amp; eſtabliſhed. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the
conſubſtantialitie of the ſonne of god. And yet neuertheleſſe,
Auſtine pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſeth, that he would neither ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> on the councel of Nyce
nor yet of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, But would be tryed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whiche ought to
bee the prooues on eyther parte. If anye man obiect the darkeneſſe of the
ſcripture, we wyll graunt that, whiche Paule ſayeth, that the naturall man,
dothe not perceyue thoſe thynges whiche procede from the ſpirite of
god.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii. d xiiii.</note> Alſo we with Peter ſaye,
that the ſcripture is not of priuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.<note place="margin">ii.
Pet. i. d xx.</note> But if y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> darknes of it be ſuch, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it cannot lighte
our minds, why dothe Chriſte referre vs onely to theſe ſcriptures, to
take cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Serch ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, ſaith he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. f. xxix.</note> Alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was deſired of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rich
&amp; vnhappy man, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was tormented in hell, that he woulde ſende ſome
manne to warne hys bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: he aunſwered, they haue Moyſes
<pb facs="tcp:11319:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the Prophetes. If they beleue not them, neither if any
manne ſhould ryſe from death, would they beleue him. Or howe did they,
which had the writings of the Apoſtles onely, when neyther bookes, nor
commentaries were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of theſame. But whereas my Lord Cardinall woulde
haue that taken for an Apoſtolike tradition, whiche hathe bene receiued of
the church at al times, in all places, and of al men. I ſee not, howe
theſe. iii. pointes maie be proued. For how great diuerſitie ſhal we
find, in the bookes of auncient fathers, yea, and euen in the verye articles of
oure faith? If theſe wordes ſhould be weyed (at all tymes, and of all men)
wher ſhall we beginn, but at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtolike church? Who ſhall be firſte
in order, but onely the Apoſtles? Whoſe liues and doings, are partly,
faithfully written by Luke, and partly, gathered out of their owne
writinges.</p>
            <p>To be ſhorte, we returne at the laſt, to the firſt
foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcriptures, ſith all truthe came from god, who
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the prophets and Apoſtles to bee interpreters &amp;
meſſengers of oure <pb facs="tcp:11319:39"/> ſaluation. In the meane time we dooe not
reiecte the councels of the fathers, as farre as they be confirmed with the
teſtimonies of the holye ſcripture. For them, as Auſtine ſayeth, the
holy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ghoſt hath ſo tempered, that it which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in ſome place is obſcurely
ſpoken, in ſome other is expreſſed more plainlye, and more at large.
And that rule chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly amonges others he geueth, whereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> we may vnderſtande
the ſcriptures, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that booke whiche he wrote of chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> doctrine, yet
there remaineth ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> doubt in this queſtion. Some me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thought, that
the will of God in theſe thinges whiche pertaine to oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, is not
fullye declared in thoſe writinges, whiche the Prophetes and Apoſtles haue
lefte vnto vs. Whiche doubte if it ſhould take any place, what a gap wer ther
opened to all miſchefe? And certes, this was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breache, by the which,
Sathan firſt pearced into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vine yard of the lord, to deſtroy it. God
true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the tune of Moyſes, with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
directed his church: &amp; in like maner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>apoſtles before thei put theyr
doctrine in writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame <pb facs="tcp:11319:40"/> by worde of mouth. But
becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men encreaſing, their noughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe encreaſed
alſo, the lorde would, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> this doctrine ſhoulde bee contayned in writinges
and monumentes. Whiche might be vnderſtoode and perceiued of al men, why
ſo? that he might confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the impudence and raſhneſſe of ſuche, as
wil ſet foorth &amp; cloke their dreames, with the name of tradition,
reuelation, and cuſtome. But if the doctrine of god be written onely in
ſome part, to what purpoſe is this remedy? Truely it can not be ſo. Iohn
ſpake of the ſcriptures, when he ſayeth, that thoſe things which are
written, are written to that ende, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beleuing them, may haue life
euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,<note place="margin">Iohn. xx.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>xi.</note> whiche he had falſlye
ſayde, yf thei themſelues had concealed any doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine neceſſary to life
and ſaluation. But Paule, when he declareth the vſe of ſcripture, &amp;
vnder the perſon of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe teacheth all miniſters, yf anye thing ſhould
haue ben added to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wuld not haue affirmed, that by them, the
man of god is made perfecte.<note place="margin">i. Timo. ii. d. xvi.</note>
Neither do we denye, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> at all times there haue ben ſomtraditions of the
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <pb facs="tcp:11319:40"/> which be not written. But thoſe were ſuche, as
pertained to the ciuil or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the churche. But foraſmuche as, many men
haue abuſed this name this great while, I thinke good to ſhewe, what
traditions ought to bee counted Apoſtolike. Whiche ſhall not be hard, yf in
iudgyng and diſcernyng them, we vſe the markes. For, fyrſt we muſt
conſyder, whether they doe agree with the doctryne of the woorde, and then,
whether they bee apte and meete to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dify<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. For it is certayne, that the
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dyd neuer inſtitute any rites and ordinaunces, whiche eyther
directly, or els in anye parte, were contrarye to theyr owne doctryne: or
myghte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe menne from ſpirituall worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng, whereof theyr owne
wrytynges beare ſufficiente recorde. If thys rule be obſerued, bothe
doctrine ſhall eaſilye be diſcerned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> traditions, &amp; alſo falſe
traditions, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true. Neyther are you ignorant how fooliſhe Tertullian
iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth their opinions, which think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles haue ouerpaſſed
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ether by word of mouth or
writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs thei haue not taught. <pb facs="tcp:11319:41"/> but we will adde more hereto.
Namely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe things, which herein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles decreed, were not
continuall. Truelye their inſtytutions paſſe all exception, yet
neuertheleſſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of charitye, they yelded ſomewhat to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
weaknes of men. As when the eating of ſuffocatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and bloud, was forbid the
Iewes. Alſo, thoſe thynges, which Paule himſelfe taught, and obſerued
in Timothe, and his own perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ac. 15. f. 25. Act. 16. a.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i Co. 16. d. xxix. i Co. 11. a
7</note> Which now truly ſhuld haue no place, but by the generall rule of
charitye, whereby, we are willed, in things indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to apply our ſelues
to our neighbours. Other ſuch like, may be gathered of their rytes, as of
kiſſing vncouering the head, which was the ſigne of authority, and other
ſuch lyke, whiche at this daye are contrarye to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cuſtomes of many
nations, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it would ſeme moſt foliſh, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men ſhould
kiſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one the other: &amp; to talke with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade vncouered, is
commonly a ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loweſt ſtate and condicion. Theſe thinges
therefore ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, before anye cuſtome be thought
Apoſtolyke.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>Alſo no man muſt grounde vppon the
authority of the Apoſtles, to trouble the church: As it hapned in the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Eaſter ſhould be kept, whiche bred
miſerable deuiſion, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Apoſtles tyme, by thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did
abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie of the churche at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to myngle
Iewiſhneſſe wyth Chriſtian religion. Of whom it is wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes
of the Apoſtles, where it was decreed by a councell, that no man ſhould lay
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yoke on mennes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Wherby, it may eaſely be perceiued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
Apoſtles could not be the authoures of ſo many ceremonies, to the which
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes: Satiſfaction, merites, and remiſſion of ſinnes wer
attributed. For they taught far otherwiſe. And ſo much they diſſented
from makyng newe ceremonies, that they gaue no place to thoſe of Moſes
lawe, of the whiche God was the author. Of thys yoke of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp;
obſeruances. Auſtine long ſince writing to Ianuarius, much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained, if
he had liued in our tyme, how would he haue lamented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Wherfore to be
ſhorte, we deſyre, that the Scripture, whiche herein is playne, maye iudge
<pb facs="tcp:11319:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> good traditions fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil, holy from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, profitable
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurtful, &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperfluous. When of theſe
ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles we are once agreed, this queſtion ſhall eaſily be
diſſolued, whether the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the church be greater, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the
woorde of god, which certes is no leſſe fonde, than if a man ſhould
doubte whether the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ought to be aboue his father, the wife aboue her
huſbande, or man aboue god. And ſure, neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church, or any godly
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, woulde moue ſuch a doubt, but wil willingly ſubmyt himſelf to her
iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Nether doth it make agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church was afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word.
For it is moſt certain, that the word which afterwards was put in wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting,
is much more auncient. For by it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceued, born &amp; bred. But
this ſaying of Auſtine, is not to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ected, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wuld not beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſcripture, vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture moued him therto. But
we muſt vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place, Auſtine ſpake of himſelf, as of
a Maniche, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whoſe erroure he was once ſeduced. I pray you, if ther
riſe ani doubt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of any writing, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go we to trie it, but to
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notary, to <pb facs="tcp:11319:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> whoſe cuſtody, al writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs &amp;
monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. Neyther therfore doth it folow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the autority of
the writyng de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth on the witnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> notarye. For of it ſelf it is
true though no mortal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beare witneſſe hereof. So truely muſt we
anſwer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thynk, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture,
dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; decrees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. The decrees of
of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels are manye tymes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary in this queſtion. But all theſe
things ſhalbe more fullye opened in diſputation &amp; conſere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. I wil
ſhewe only reaſon, confirmed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autority of certayn auncient &amp;
allowed fathers. Chriſt himſelf, gaue ſo much authority to the doctrine
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets, whom he had ſent afore, that by theyr witneſſe he would
confirme his doctrine. Paul al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, ſuffred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo to
do, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſearche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, to know whether he had
taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly.<note place="margin">Ac. xvii. c. xi.</note> Peter allowed that
ſelfeſame reaſon.<note place="margin">ii. Peter. ii. d. xix.</note> They
therfore, which boaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelnes to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicars of Chriſt, &amp; the
ſucceſſors of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; Paule, ought not to refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ca. ix. li. ii.</note> Truely Ierome vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hieremy,
ſayth: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> error of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers nor <pb facs="tcp:11319:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> of our
aunceſters, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of the Scriptures is to be folowed. Chriſofto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vpon the .xxiiii. Chapter of Mathew the 49. Homelye, erpounding thys place.
Thoſe that be in Iury, let them flye to the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes, ſayeth: that is,
thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be Chriſtians, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flye to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And again.
Wherefore doth he in this tyme, wil al Chriſtians to fly to the Scriptures?
Bicauſe in thys tyme, ſince hereſy inuaded the churche, there can be no
other proofe of true Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, neither any other refuge for Chriſtians
minding to knowe the true fayth, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine Scriptures. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it
appeared by many ſignes, which was the church of Chriſt, and whiche it of
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentiles. But now whoſoeuer wil ſeke it, can by no other meanes
diſcerne which is the true church of Chriſte, but onely by the Scriptures.
Alſo he ſaieth further. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore be wylling to knowe the true
church of Chriſt, howe ſhould he know it in ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyon, but
only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures? Yet further therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther ſhuld
be ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter dayes, therfore doth Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitye <pb facs="tcp:11319:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; ſuch as be
willing to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o other
thing but the Scriptures. Other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e any other changes, they
ſhal likely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſh, not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, which is the
true ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rch and ſo ſhal they fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of defolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy places of the churche. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in his moralls writeth thus. If,
whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne, (as the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ayth) and faith
commeth by hearing, and hearing by the worde of God: whatſoeuer is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
Scripture inſpired of God, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n. Alſo, in the Sermon of the
confeſſion of faith. If God be faithful in al his words and hys
commaundementes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>me and ſtable, for euer, done in truth &amp; iuſtice, to
reiect any thing that is written, or to bring in any thing not written, is a
ſweruing from fayth &amp; manifeſt pride. Thus much was ſpoken of the
churche, her ſignes, authority and ſucceſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lordes, and
Biſhops, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other, which heard theſame very attentiuely. But
bicauſe hys oration had bin already ſomewhat lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, it ſemed good then to
entreate nothing of the <pb facs="tcp:11319:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſupper. Wherfore Beza medeſtly
excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng hymſelf, &amp; declaryng alſo, that we wer ready to ſhew a
reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> article, and as much as lay in vs to ſatiſfy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they
would commaund vs forthwith to doe it. When Beza had ended, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynal
beckned to Spenſa to ſpeak, and to anſwere our reaſons. He proteſtyng
with many woordes, that he had long wyſhed for this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, &amp;
diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neuer lyked alwaies contrary to thoſe cruel
puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which had lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tymes bene vſed toward them, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that
thoſe thinges were true, which we had ſayd of the churche, her ſygnes and
ſucceſſion. If we had ſo taught, and ſpoken at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, we
ſhould neuer haue neded to haue come to this controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy. But whereas we
ſpake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> callyng into the churche, he muche maruelled, by whoſe
authoritye, or by what cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng we entred into the churche, and toke vpon vs to
teache. Foraſmuch as we wer not inſtituted by any ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, neyther they
at any tyme had layd theyr handes vpon vs. And hereof he gathered, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we wer
no good paſtors For by ordinary meanes (quoth he) you wer not called, and
muche leſſe by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. <pb facs="tcp:11319:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> For extraordinarye
voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt bee proued eyther by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as the callyng of Moſes
was, who was rayſed vp of God, to delyuer his people: or els by the
witneſſe of the ſcripture, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> callyng of Iohn, whoſe vocation is
plainlye proued by a terte of Malachye, you want bothe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it foloweth,
that youre miniſterye is vnlawfull. But as concernyng trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the
interpretyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yf there ryſe any controuerſye, we ought
to referre it (quothe he) to the ordinary ſucceſſours: as thoſe, to
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſt is promiſed, and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of God for the ſame
cauſe.</p>
            <p>He brought foorth the exaumples of the olde Prieſtes and
Leuites, whiche in tymes paſte, in doubtful matters gaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel,
&amp; to whoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, the people were ſo bounde to ſtande, that
from theyr decree, it was not lawfull for them to ſwarue, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the
ryghte hande, neyther yet on the left. And that we had many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by
tradition, whiche no manne doubtes of, no, not we oure ſelues. As y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the
father is without beginnyng, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon equall in ſubſtance to him, alſo
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yong <pb facs="tcp:11319:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> children ought to be Baptiſed, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was a
virgin after her deliuerance, &amp; ſuch lyke. So he affirmed, that thoſe
thinges, which are deſcended vnto vs from the auncient fathers, albeit they
bee not written, yet are certainelye to be beleued, and no leſſe to be
allowed, than if they were confirmed by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scriptures. That
what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is decreed by generall councels is certain, and that they can not
erre in doctrine. But as to that, which is cyted out of Auſtine, that the
firſt counſels ar amended by the later, that he ſaid neuer was in
doctrine. That there were onely three kept before Auſtines time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The
Nicene councell againſt the Arrians, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councel of Conſtantinople
againſt the Macedonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the firſt counſel of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus againſt
Neſtorius, none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was afterwardes amended. He denied the hiſtory
of Paphuntius, as a thyng doubtful to be credited and further ſayd that it
perteined not to the purpoſe. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte to geue the Cardinall
occaſion, which ſeking by al meanes to breake of the conference, willed him
to entreate of the ſupper: he came to that queſtion, <pb facs="tcp:11319:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and with few wordes entreated, of the preſence of the body of Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
bred. And he red to vs, certaine places out of the bokes of Caluine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aling
neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the name of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tour, ſaying that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>erua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>led, if we
would ſwarue from hym, to whom we geue moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie aboue the reſt,
&amp; about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of his tale, he gaue vs thoſe places to read.</p>
            <p>Afore we anſwered Spenſa, a Monk of that order, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are
clothed all in white, whoſe name they ſay was Xantus, ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped forth,
enflamed with deſire of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as though he were aggrieued that
Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa had talked ſomwhat graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and modeſtly, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to powre out his
ſtomake and not able to ſtay any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, wuld not let vs anſwer, til we
had firſt heard him. Then, he began to repeate thoſe things, which Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa
had already ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at large ſawcig y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoffes &amp; tauntes,
which he ſemed to eſteme, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greateſt orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; grace of his
talke. For vs he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared, both to other aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, &amp; alſo to
the Anabaptiſts, but at the laſt he became ſo mad, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers, he affirmed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is <pb facs="tcp:11319:46"/> more ſure, than of the ſcripture. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſcriptures (quoth he) may by diuers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations bee wried ſondry
waies. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ciprian, with the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phricans, was deceiued in
this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſayd. Chriſt ſayeth not, I am y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cuſtom. But, I am the
waye, truthe and lyfe. And that this his ſaying, heretikes dyd afterwardes
commonly abuſe. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the authoritie of Tertullian, of the
preſcriptions of heretikes, impery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, &amp; euen like a maiſter of
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcooles. (I will not ſaye foolyſhly) willyng Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, to reade the
place by hym alledged, twice or thrice, Tertullians wordes be theſe. They
alledge the ſcriptures, and with theſe their impudence, at the fyrſt moue
awaye. Alſo that the diſputation with ſcriptures, nothyng auaileth,
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man do altogether, eyther turne his ſtomake, or his brayne.
And again. Therfore we muſt not appeale to the ſcriptures, neither contend
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, by whom there is eyther no victorye to be atchieued, or if there be
any, it is verye vncertain. Furthermore Xa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god, otherwiſe
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he intended (for that was his term) deliuered his doctryne in
<pb facs="tcp:11319:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> writing, abuſig the autority of Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, or of
the author of the imperfecte work writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mathew. And falſlye touching
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proeme of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> work, wher ther is no ſuche thyng red. For theſe bee the
wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author. After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, was falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depth of ſin, it was neceſſary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then a law ſhuld be writen,
&amp; the tables geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; warning &amp; threates by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this we
ſee, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not only to the holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
the new alſo. For Chriſt left nothing in writyng to hys apoſtles, but in
ſtede of writing, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt He
(quoth he) wil teach you al thinges. Then he added alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but alſo
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of god wherof came al
traditions. Alſo for the rule to diſcerne traditions, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not only the
word, but alſo the nature &amp; cuſtom is to be conſidred. Accordyng to
the ſaying of Paule the .i. Corint. xi. Nature it ſelf teacheth you. And
again, neyther, let vs not haue ſuch a cuſtome neyther the exaumples of the
church of god, to be ſhorte, he rehearſed the ſame that Spenſa had
afo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:47"/>Hereto Beza aunſwered modeſtly at large, that to
haue one ſelfe ſame tale doubled of diuers, is not mete for that conference
or diſputation, wherein any good ende or concorde ſhould be ſought For
that of muche matter heaped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the witts of man are confounded, ſo as
therof, no good thing may aryſe but confuſion. That euen by their own
iudgementes, if they had at any tyme vſed diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this order could not
be allowed. Neuertheleſſe he hoped, that ſo farre as his memory would
ſerue hym, to reherſe their reaſons, he would light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatiſfy them.
And therwithal, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Queene and the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobles,
hereafter to take ſome better order for their conference.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore, wheras Spenſa had ſayd, that he much
meruayled, that we toke vpon vs to teache, foraſmucheas the ordinary
ſucceſſors had neuer layde handes vpon vs: he anſwered, that this is
not the chiefe ſigne of lawfull calling For the chiefe and ſubſtantiall
partes be, the inquiſition of learning and lyfe, and choyſe and election.
Theſe be the ordinary meanes. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which although <pb facs="tcp:11319:47"/> the
outwarde ceremonies of laying on handes, be not adioyned, yet the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
is lawful notwithſtanding. And that we, which wer there preſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende
our doctrine, and the reſt of oure felowes, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted not alſo the third mark.
And neded not to ſtay on that poynte, foraſmuch as we were both choſen
and confirmed. For handes were layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, and we lawfully preſented to
oure churches, which accepted our miniſtery if it be obiected, that thoſe
of whom we were inſtituted and which layed their handes on vs, had no
autority of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſucceſſors, neyther were choſen of the
people: the anſwere is ready, that thinges being in ſuch confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and
the eccleſiaſticall order diſordred, we dyd not ſtay for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> layeng on
of their handes whoſe vicious lyfe, ſuperſtition, &amp; falſe doctrine,
we haue alwayes reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. For in vaine ſhould we haue ſought, to haue
bin allowed of them, whiche wyth deadly hate purſued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truth, &amp; the
defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders therof. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wanted not the preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophetes, to
who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none were more deadly enemies, than the Prieſtes, foraſmuch as thei
themſelues wer turned out of kind &amp; no longer reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <pb facs="tcp:11319:48"/>
their office therfore, foraſmuche as againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chiefly, the lord had
ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the prophets, they ought not to ſeke for, at their hands the
confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> autority, which they had receyued of god. Nether did they
intrude the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues into the miniſtery but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei had once the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of god, thei wer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the peril of theyr liues, to
execute theſame. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſame, we in theſe our times, ought to do
alſo. Furthermore, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> extraordinary calling, is not alwaies proued by
miracles. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which we read of Moſes, &amp; the ſignes ſhewed by him,
hapned not ſo, in all the reſt. For by what miracles did Eſay Daniel,
Amos, &amp; Zachary proue theyr calling? Or Paulus afore he did execute his
charge. Did he ſtay for the layi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds? but to proue himſelf an
apoſtle he did not ſo much cite his miracles, of the which he had great
ſtore, as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fruite of his preachyng, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe
people who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord had turned at his cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling. For writing to the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
he ſaith: You are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeale of my apoſtleſhip in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lord.<note place="margin">Cor. ix.</note> Theſame truely ſay, of ſo gret a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, as
by our preching haue, rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt al the power of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:48"/> nether ſeke we any other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our calling &amp;
miniſtery. For the power &amp; vertue of god hath ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhewed it
ſelf, foraſmuch, as nether pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fier, baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor death could
ſtay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame. But quoth Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa, ſhew me but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one example w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in
theſe .xv. C. yeares, like to your caſe. Although (quoth Beza) al
hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories are not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet I donbie not but there may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſom.
But if ther be none, it is no inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god in our daies hath
done y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, which he neuer did afore. Afterwards we cam to traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which
Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa made equal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcripture, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus preferred aboue it, as
more certain tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. But to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Paul, which reuoketh vs to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
ſcripturs Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwerd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul ſpeketh general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of doctrine.
Which forth w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red not of vs only, but of an other ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larly
wel learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was there preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Moreouer we ſaid, it was new
&amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Xa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus wold haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s more cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſcripture, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, may be vncertayne.
For, what fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal our faith haue, if we doubt of it? neither is it
therefore incertain bicauſe many times me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply it, mangle it, &amp;
abuſe it. For the <pb facs="tcp:11319:49"/> truthe abides alway one, which though it be
ſomtymes darkned, yet continueth her force euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt. Neither,
bicauſe heretikes abuſe it, ought we therefore, the leſſe to fly to it.
What wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he doth vs, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring of Anabaptiſtes &amp; other diueliſh
ſectes, our writings wel teſtify. They admit onely ſom part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. We accept &amp; allow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole: they credit new reuelations. We
ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche thynges are out of place, ſithe Chriſte hath manifeſted
al things fully vnto vs. As to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus warned
Beza, twice or thrice to read it: I (quoth Beza) haue read it more than xx.
tymes, &amp; am ſo well aſſured, that you ſhall finde it as I ſaye,
as I perfectly know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhal neuer finde in Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, that which
you in his name haue falſely alleged: But do not deny, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian did
manye tymes paſſe his bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Neuertheleſſe, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider towhat
ende he ſpake it, you ſhal perceiue, how lightly, this which you thynke to
make ſo much w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, ſhalbe anſwered. For this was his purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we
ſhould not in vaine reaſon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heretikes. As Paule cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaileth vs, after
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt or ſeconde ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition <pb facs="tcp:11319:49"/> to leaue them. But what
maner of heretikes were thoſe? Suche as beig conuicted of their hereſy by
the worde of god, tryfled in vayne. What were the traditions, whiche he layde
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? Such as are conteyned in the writinges of the Apoſtles, and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn to the chiefe articles of our fayth, and which the whole church
profeſſed. Fyrſt therfore, we ſhould haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted by the ſame
worde, that if we be in any erroure, we might thereby bee withdrawen from it.
But to bee confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by tradition whiche is neither Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical, nor yet
grounded on their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truely is aſmuch, as to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gate to all
deceite and vtterly to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the certaintye of oure faith. But why doth
Tertullian himſelf vpbrayde the heretikes? ſaying: Let them beleue the
ſcriptures, if they can do it beleuig agaynſt the ſcriptures: except we
ought to flye to them, and by them confute all errors? If theſe rytes whyche
at thys daye our aduerſaries haue brought in, were Apoſtolike, the churche
would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue vſed them. Neither ſhould they haue had ſo late
beginning. Now, <pb facs="tcp:11319:50"/> foraſmuche as the authors of them are wel
knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; deſcribed in hiſtories, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, it cannot be ſaid, that
they came firſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles. Falſly alſo is the name of
traditions refrained to thoſe things, which are deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hande to
hande, in as muche as this woorde <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
is referred, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are writen. Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refuteth thoſe
that taught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apoſtles had not ſufficiently inſtructed vs in al
things, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei might leaue a place for new tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as things reuealed by
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt. Thei are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſay (quoth he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles knew al,
but neuertheles, put not al in writing. In both pointes blaming chriſt, as
though he had either inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly inſtructed his apoſtles, or els had
choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch ſimple me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as were not able to vtter their mindes in
writing. For what ſober ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles wer ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in
any thing who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord appointed as maiſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles therfore we muſt fly, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to preach. But how
ſhall we be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their doctrine, but by their wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings? Was not
vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for this cauſe? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might deliuer and
<pb facs="tcp:11319:50"/> write vnto vs, al things neceſſarye for our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not
to leaue vs douting, or vncertain. And herby is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſtom
eaſily diſcuſſed, which was earſt aleged, where he ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
Chriſt left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in writing to his apoſtles. Wuld he therfore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei
ſhuld write nothing? No ſure. But therfore he taught them, therfore he
reueled it vnto them by his ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame doctrine once written
might remain for euer. But thei taught ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>things which are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in
their writings. Neither y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truely do we deny. But we ſaie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is
nothing pertaining to our ſaluation. Whyche they haue not left in writing,
other thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne rites, &amp; ciuill dyſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, they might
eaſily teach by worde of mouth. But becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame chaunge, according to
time &amp; place, they woulde not bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> then our conſciences therwith. As to
the obiection of the names of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten, conſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiality, trinity,
bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of children, although the playne names &amp; wordes be not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſcriptures, yet the thinges themſelues, that is to wit, the ſence and
grounde. Whereof the names are gathered, is playnelye <pb facs="tcp:11319:51"/>
expreſſed and ſhewed in the ſcripture. Theſe thinges were long
debated, and ſometymes the talke interrupted, Xan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſpake muche, and
affirmed a great while, that the virginitie of Mary after her deliuerance,
coulde not bee proued by the ſcriptures. Neither yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yong children ought
to be baptiſed. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, bothe were proued by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of
the ſcripture. But he ceaſſed not to bable after the maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boniſtes, as though he ſhoulde wynne the victorie, with triflyng and
talking. His talke litle liked ſo honorable anau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as it, that was full
of bitternes, ſharpeneſſe and ſtomake. Our men in the meane tune,
modeſtly ſtayd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And albeit manye of our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
ſpake at once confuſedly, yet we counted it better to for beare than to be
counted lyke to ſuche trouble ſome tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers. At this alteration the
Cardynall ſtepped in, and as though this queſtion had ben ſufficiently
debated, made an end therof. Or rather, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he coulde no longer beare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
proud &amp; inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t talke of Xa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus he brake of his talk. Hereof,
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sorhoniſts, as if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater had ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, or
ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence geuen on <pb facs="tcp:11319:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> theyr ſide, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vain arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>waded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had won the victorye. Neither is it any
marueyle, for neither could we anſwer many of theyr reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which they
ſpake all at once, ſo that we could not vnderſtand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nether would we
interrupt the Cardinal in his talke. But he, taking on him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of a iudge
dyd cloſelye conclude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whatſoeuer is written, ought to be referred to
the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the charch: &amp; that her trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wer in all pointes to
be obſerued. Afterwardes, he turned his talke to the Lordes ſupper,
affirming &amp; proteſtyng that he woulde goe no farther, tyll we agreed of
that article. For this (ſayd he) is the controuerſye that troubles moſt
men. And ſayd further, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled him to talke
therof. For y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in our fyrſt metyng, we had plainlye fhewed our mynde therof,
which nowe filled al Fraunce with diuers &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous rumour, and farther
was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, and ſette abrode. He obiected vnto vs, the confeſſion of
Awgſpurge, &amp; aſked, whether we wold ſubſcribe ther to. We aſked
agayne, whether they woulde bee contente to allowe it in all pointes, then they
beganne to trifle.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:52"/>Furthermore, they obiected other o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of certain
miniſters of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, which they ſaid wer ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither wer
they aſhamed, to deſyre &amp; intreate vs, to ſubſcribe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was done for a pollicy, to thintente, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if we denied ſo to do, he might
ſet vs at ſtrife with the Germans, and make vs to be hated of them. And if
we did agre, then they as conquerours ſhoulde try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer vs: and make a
commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ieſt of vs, as of light and vndiſcrete perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne
our opinion. To auoid this doubt, we anſwered that we came thither, to
defende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confeſſion of oure faith and had no other commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or
authoritie of our churches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therfore we required that we might folowe the
order of our confeſſion: and that euerye article, might be ſeuerally and
diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weyed, ſo that it mighte plainlye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, wherein we agree,
and wherein we diſagree. For bothe the order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and alſo the waye
to concorde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that thoſe thinges, whiche be playneſt and
eaſieſt, ſhould firſt be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Furthermore, foraſmuch as the
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes depend vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine: It <pb facs="tcp:11319:52"/> is moſt
neceſſary, firſt to reaſon of it. With al this we nothing preuailed.
For the Cardinal continued in his purpoſe. We ſaw alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he attempted
this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we with inequall hande, might departe the conferre, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame
might ſeeme to be broken of, by our ſtubborneſſe. Which we thought good
by al meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therfore, we deſired to haue their writing to the
which they would haue vs ſubſcribe, that we might deliberate therof. Ther
with all they brought forth a copie of the article of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſupper,
take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as they ſaid) out of the confeſſion, of Awgſpurge. But differing
neuerthe leſſe: much therfrom, as it may wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the reading
thereof. For this it was, with a ſtedfaſt faith we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that in
the moſt reuerend ſacrament of the Lordes body and bloud, truly, real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and ſacramentally, the true bodye &amp; bloude of Chriſt is offred, to the
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicantes, and receiued by them. Herto they added, the confeſſion of
certayne miniſters of Wittenberge, ſet forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the yere of our of our
lord god. 1559. So we departed for that day, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was deferred till
the morowe. <pb facs="tcp:11319:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> Wherfore when we perceiued, that by this
requeſte they minded, to driue vs to this inconuentence, that eyther we
ſhould denie our own confeſſion, or els breake of the conference,
returnyng at the laſt, and calling on the name of god we determined rather to
take the moſt vnequall and bniuſt conditions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could be offred, than to
geue any occaſyon, wherby it might ſeme, that we fled the conference.
Therfore, the nexte day we prepared our ſelues to aunſwere, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng
alwayes, when we ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to come, when it was ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed to
vs from the Queene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſame was deferred for twoo dayes. In the meane
tyme, diuers tales were ſpred of vs, as that we were ouercome, and could not
proue our miniſtery lawfully, and our aduerſaries reioyced as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors,
as though our hearts fainted, to be ſhort, thei criu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phed afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory
But this theyr myrth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. For ii daies after, at oure returne we
brought forth an a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer, more at large, &amp; more perfect, to thoſe things
which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wer ouer paſſed, &amp; vſed ſuch meanes as we could, to
auoid the pollicy of oure <pb facs="tcp:11319:53"/> aduerſaries. It Beza reherſed in
wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tig. The effect of it was this: That we greatly maruelled, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wheras of
late we had ſo aboundantly shewed, what is the church, what be her marks
&amp; how great her autority, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any reaſonable manne might be ſatiſfied
ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Yet neuer the leſſe, nothing was ſaide againſt it, but onely
demaunded of vs, by what power we do adminiſter the worde of GOD &amp;
ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And yet nothing ouerpaſſed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> might make our cauſe odious
&amp; hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. For to what purpoſe it was ſpoken we could not as yet wel
perceue bicauſe we came not thither to adminiſter the word or ſacraments.
But if an accompt ſhalbe demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of vs of thoſe thinges which her to fore
we haue don, thei muſt underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges vs, there are two ſorts of
miniſters. One of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teach in foren cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which theyr
cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is allowed. And of thoſe it cannot iuſtly be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded here,
wherfore they be miniſters. Another ſort is of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
goſpel in this realm: whom we thought not to be ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for hyther, to geue an
accompt of their callig, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer &amp; diſpute of doctrine.
Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <pb facs="tcp:11319:54"/> they might ſeme to bee ſent for to plead their
cauſe, as for ſom crime. Which we cannot think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Queene or nobles in
any wiſe minded. And yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame be required, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colour of
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference &amp; reaſoning, it is verye far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meanes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord,
&amp; reconcilement. For we cannot enter into ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp;
demaundes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out the greate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops, &amp; other the Lords
of ſpiritualtie. But none of vs all at anye time minded it, but purpoſed
onelye to proſecute this holy purpoſe. I pray you if two parties agree to
conferre, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes the one demaunde of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By what nower do
you this? muſt it not needes enſue, that by ſuche que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions they
ſhal fall at bariance. As for example, ſetting a part the biſhops, and
other the ſpiritualtie of this realm, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are lothe to offende, let vs
admytte that ſome ſtraunge byſhop enquireth of vs, by what authoritye, we
miniſter the woorde and Sacramentes? And we againe aſke of hym, by whom he
was choſen and inſtitute? Whether by the voices of the elders of his
church, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were deſyred of the people, <pb facs="tcp:11319:54"/> whether there
wer any inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of his life &amp; doctrine? He woulde ſoone ſay
yea. But he wuld ſoone be proued a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lter. Whereof we deſier no other
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciece which heare vs, &amp; know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole matter
perfectly. If he would obſect againſt vs, that we are no miniſters,
becauſe we wante the laying on of hands: we would reply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is no
biſhop, becauſe in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of hym, thoſe things wer not
obſerued, which are appointed, for the chief &amp; ſubſtantiall poyutes,
by the law of god. And when our talke wer more, whether perhappes we would goe
far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſay in this ſort. You boaſte of the laying on of handes,
which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer lacketh, you thynk no perfect mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter: what if you wante
the two other points which are the chiefeſt? Namely, inquiſition of lyfe
&amp; learning, &amp; the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elders of your church? may ye not
then, much leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we, bragge of the name of a paſtor? It was decreed
by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councel of Chalcedon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop, or prteſt,
ſhoulde bee fruſtrate, &amp; of no force, which is not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially
appointed to ſome one churche. <pb facs="tcp:11319:55"/> And foraſmuche as they would
haue it doyde to the iniury of hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ordayneth it, much more may we obiect
theſame, agaynſt the biſhop, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus reaſoneth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, inaſmuch he
is deſtitute of the two chiefeſt conditions, preſcribed by the
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle.<note place="margin">i. Tim. iii a. Titus. i</note> Another thyng
alſo, may bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hereto, which we ſpeak vnwilling, neuertheleſſe we
are enforced therto, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery man maye perceiue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of
our vocation may not be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out great peril. If we ſhould aſk of
that ſame biſhop, who layde their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des on him, or whether he bought it
not with money, what would he aunſwer? He would deny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he bought it, and he
would ſay that thoſe biſhops layd ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds on him which had autority therto
of the church. Again, if we ſhould enquire how much his authoritie coſt
hym, he would ſay he bought it not, but yet he woulde confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
gaue ſome thouſandes of crownes. As though he ſhoulde ſaye, I boughte
not the bread, but the corne, wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bread was made. This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonyng,
if it ſhould be parted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels &amp; cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the
chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, woulde ſhame a greate many by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops &amp; paſtours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:55"/>And ſure we would not enter therein, leaſt any
man ſhould be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded therby. Neyther wyll we yet touche it, or ſek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to
reuenge oure ſelues, only we mynde to ſhew, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we dyd of late purpoſely
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſhortly &amp; briefly, to thoſe thyngs, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wer layd agaynſt
vs, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we woulde haue all gently and myldly handled. But as for the Lords
ſupper, we ſpake more ſparely therof, bearyng with the infirmitte of
ſome, whiche not accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doctrine, are wont to be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
aſſoone as they heare anye thing, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is ſtrange, or vnwo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we had rather, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſhuld learne theſame, out
of the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Doctors of the church, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> by vs, which we
hoped ſhould haue com to paſſe, if my lord Cardinal had kepte his
promiſſe. For he promiſed ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, to inſtruct vs chiefly in this
article of the lords ſupper, out of their writings whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wrote therof, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
in .v. C. yeres after Chriſt: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we would now agree to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the
light, if it appered, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſame was hitherto hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. To
ſatiſfye this our expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or rather the expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an infinite
nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſepe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated <pb facs="tcp:11319:56"/> this article, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others verye
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, &amp; gaue it to vs alone. And requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs to ſubſcribe to
it: ſaying y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the conference would be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, yf we ſhould
plead our cauſe in priſon, you woulde ſcarce vſe ſuche talke
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, as to ſaye ſubſcribe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or els we condemne you.
Certainly, this is no part of your charge. For that office, which ye now
profeſſe, requyreth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> if we walk in error, you ſhould reduce vs, beyng
once co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict therof, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way and exhort vs with wholeſom doctrine. And
chiefly thoſe, which offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to yelde an accompt of theyr fayth,
(by the ſcriptures.) And truly, if thys kinde of condemnation be ſtraunge,
certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muche more ſtraunge is the way and meanes, wherby you procede to
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame. We came together here chieflye for .ii. cauſes. Firſt, to render
an accompte to god, to you, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole worlde of oure fayth. Not to
trauel for gods cauſe, the kings, &amp; the whole kingdom, &amp; to fynde
ſome way and meanes, wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles late ſtirred in religion may be
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed. Now if we bee reiected, or dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out leaue or
liberty to diſpute <pb facs="tcp:11319:56"/> whatſoeuer ſhalbe done vnto vs, ſhal
be declared to all Chriſtendome: &amp; the olde tumultes ſhalbe nothyng
appeaſed, as thei know right wel, which go about to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter
did only belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are here preſent, truly at your ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp;
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out peril, as farre (as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may iudge) you might dayly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs. But you
muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtand here, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of al thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, not onely in this realme, but euen in Swicerla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
Poole, Germany, England and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, whiche all looke for ſom certayne
&amp; happy end of this aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly. What may they thinke, when in ſtede of
diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; conference, which was promiſed vs, they ſhall
vnderſtande that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenth part of one article was offred to vs, wyth this
addition? Subſcribe to this, or els go no further. And yf we doe
ſubſcrybe what ſhall you be the better? They that ſente vs, wyll
deſyre to knowe whether we were compelled therto by force, or els conuict, by
good &amp; ſure argumente. So what els ſhall happen of this order, which
you now begin to take, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gret offence and grudge? wee beſeche the Queene
therfore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe wyll not ſuffer <pb facs="tcp:11319:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:58"/> this holy
purpoſe, to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> certain learned mete men, be
choſen out, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will wyllynglye conferrs with vs. Neuertheleſſe, leaſt
we ſhould ſeme to anſwer nothyng, to thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that haue ben
obiected agaynſt vs, whatſoeuer M. Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa gaue vs writen, out of Caluins
booke, we receyue &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. But as to the article, whyche my Lord Cardinal
offred vs, take or rather gelded out of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Awgſpurge: we
ſay, there are many thynges therin to be conſidred. Firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſhould haue ben offred vnto vs. For it is agaynſt reaſon,
to proffer vs one article without the reſte. Then we woulde knowe whether of
theyr owne heads priuately (whiche we are lothe to think, neuertheleſſe we
woulde gladlye knowe the truth therof) or elles in the name of all the Lords,
they offer vs the confuſion of Augſpurge: that al doutes taken away, we may
more freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre. For ſo it would come to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thanks ſhuld
generally be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to god, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> my L. Cardinal, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
lords, reiect tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which now, by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of al
churches, aſwell in <pb facs="tcp:11319:58"/> Germany, as in other realmes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.
If we be required to ſubſcribe to any writing, it is mete alſo, that the
Cardinal of Loraine, in the name of al his, ſhould ſubſcribe theſame
alſo. That the churches by whom we were ſente, may perceiue, that we met
not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitably about theſe matters. If my Lord Cardinall, wil
conſtantlye perſeuer in that mynde, that he wil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the whole
confeſſion of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, we hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall come nier, and at the
laſt to that point, that we ſhal eaſely ſatiſfy you: And ſhewe a
ready way to peace and concorde. In the meane tyme, we affirme, that Chriſte
is preſent in the vſe of his Supper, and there doth after, geue, and
exhibite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, his body and bloud, by the power and operation of the holy
ghoſt. And if we do receiue, eate &amp; drinke ſpiritually and by fayth,
the ſelfe ſame bodye that dyed for vs, and the ſelfe ſame bloud, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
was ſhed for our ſaluation. That we may be bones of his bones, and fleſh
of his fleſh. And that we may be quickned thereby, and receiue, whatſoeuer
is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our ſaluation. We deſired <pb facs="tcp:11319:59"/> alſo of the
Queene, if this ſatiſfied her not, bicauſe it is hard, to entreate of
ſo great a myſtery with fewe words, that we might ſpeake therof, in more
large and ample ſort. And that we were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to do it, whenſoeuer the
Cardinall of Loraine, would ſhew his authorities out of the olde doctours.
Moreouer, we earneſtly deſired, that there mighte bee ſome equall, and
tolerable order of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or diſputation, taken, ſuche as we
deſired, euen from the beginning. And we proteſt that therby it ſhould
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to all men, that we came not thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſtirre contention, but
rather, to finde meanes of concord, in ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue. For we deſired
nothing els, but that thoſe thinges reſtored to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lordes Supper, which
were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from it, and taking away thoſe thinges that were il added, it
might be reſtored to the olde perfection. Which to compaſſe, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed
not to ſpare our liues, but in ſo good a cauſe, to yelde and render oure
liues and heartes, to God, the king, the nobles, and the common quietneſſe,
as well of this realme, as of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. With thys oration oure
aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries <pb facs="tcp:11319:59"/> were greatly amaſed, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the
firſt parte thereof, wherby they ſawe the glory of their ſucceſſion
and callig ſtained. For they could haue heard nothing, more greuous or
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to them. Therfore the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall freatting, &amp; much diſquieted,
ſaid: we were now come to a good poynt, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we were not content to inuade the
dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine of Prieſtes. But we muſte alſo touche the kyngs maieſtie. For
he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyly wroughte to bring vs in hate, as though we had accuſed the king,
for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the elections of Biſhops &amp; Abbates, as though the fault
were in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> kyng that none of them were choſen, but as for themſelues, they
ſayd, they were ordeined and inſtituted, by the king, to whom the people
had geuen al their right and power therin. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if we would diſproue
that, we muſt ſpeake to the kyng, to whom it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to maintayne his
lawes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces. And that we were ignoraunte how they were ordeined,
when all the people wer came together by the knol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of bells, and therefore
geſſed, of thinges that we knew not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:60"/>To conclude all hys talke was full of tauntes,
whereby he thought to kyndle the Queenes wrath towardes vs, as though, we
accuſed the kyng of Tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. But that ſlaunder was eaſely auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For
it was forthwith ſhewed, that therby is the confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the true
eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall order and ſtate, made muche more manifeſt. For that
kinges were fame to ſet to their handes, to reforme that horrible diſorder,
which ambition, enuy, contention and ſuch like, had lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme bredde amonges
the Canonicall Prieſtes, Monkes, and all the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
eccleſiaſticall order. And could by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes remedy that ſore,
than by taking from them the liberty of choyſe which ſo long tyme, they had
ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and beaſtly abuſed. And as to their common forme of
ordaining Biſhops, and paſtours, it is right well knowen, what a ieſt it
is, and therefore we wyll waſte no time in ſpeaking of it. For we entred
not into that matter, to handle it at large, but onely to ſhew that oure
myniſtery, which in thys ruine, and ſo great confuſion, of the church,
the Lord hath rayſed, is lawful, and vnworthely <pb facs="tcp:11319:60"/> mocked at. You
your ſelues began firſt to talke thereof, (quoth the Cardinall) you firſt
inuaded our flocke. We came not into your garriſons, but you into oures,
Neither would I wiſh you ſhuld thinke your ſelues as good as we, nor
talke as ye woulde to youre felowes. Our eſtate is ſomewhat higher than
yours. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſaw him ſpeake cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this ſort, we thought good to
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him no longer, leaſt we mighte ſeme oure ſelues to haue hindered
the diſputation. Then he began againe to be earneſt on vs, to know ſome
reaſon why we would not ſubſcribe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Augſpurge.
We anſwered him againe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it was vnreaſonable, to require y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> of vs,
which do not allow it in al pointes. But, if they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues would firſt
ſubſcribe, it would be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eaſier way to reconcile vs to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we
knowe not, whether he of hys owne head, or els by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente of al the
reſt, did put in that bill, whiche he would haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. I (quoth
the Cardinall) am ſworne to no man. And therefore, will I neither
ſubſcribe to the confeſſion of Awgſpurge, neyther yet to you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:61"/>And yet I wil be ready to ſubſcribe both to them
and you, if you thinke truely. And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I offer nothing to you of mine own head,
theſe my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, can witneſſe. Which when he ſayd
he turned his body, towardes the reſte of the Cardinals and Biſhops. Which
neither graunted to his ſaying by word or geſture, nor greatly withſtode
it. Therfore, for aſmuche as they woulde not ſubſcribe, we ſayd, they
coulde not require it of vs. This done and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the Cardinall entred
into talke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes Supper, and ſet his common doctors to vs. Maſter
Spenſa, began to vrge the preſence of the body of Chriſt in his Supper,
ſo that he encloſed the body within the bread. And ſaid, it culd no
otherwiſe be imagined, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt nedes be ioyned with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread,
and reproued vs, as though we ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from our maſter Caluine, whoſe
boke he had alleaged. We ſayd, we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym in nothing, and that we
were ready to ſubſcribe to all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of that boke. Then he vrged
the name of ſubſtaunce whiche Caluine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſeth. We anſwered, that we wont
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o <pb facs="tcp:11319:61"/> vſe that terme, leaſt men ſhould thinke, that we fain
either ſome new or ymagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nary body, or ſome phantaſtical recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
therof, but neuertheleſſe, that we are no otherwiſe made partakers, of
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body, than by ſayth, and power of the holy ghoſt. Hereto the right
reuerende maſter Peter Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, added many thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and according to his
ſinguler lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, beſides many other thinges, which perteine to the order
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church he handled this queſtion alſo, ſhortlye, plainly, and
eloquently. He anſwered alſo diuers things which both the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, and
Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa had obiected in their orations in the firſt meting, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thoſe things, which concerne the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and amendmente of counſels.
Which ſo pricked the Cardinal, that he would no more reply vnto hym. And
whyles he was handling and declaring diuers matters more playnly, bicauſe he
ſpake ſomewhat after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Cardinal roſe, and ſayd in
a great chafe, that he would talke wyth hys own countrey me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And yet marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
ſpake ſo plainly &amp; diſtinctly, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> not only y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Cardinal being
ſkilful in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, <pb facs="tcp:11319:62"/> but alſo euery ignoraunt man,
myghte well perceiue him. Spenſa ſomewhat talked to him, herefore
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending him aboue the reſt, that no man this day li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that had written
more largely or copiouſly of this queſtion than he. Afore Spenſa was
anſwered: a Spanyarde, one of thoſe, that call themſelues Ieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wites,
deſired that he might haue leaue to ſpeake. His talke was ſharp, &amp;
bitter and nothing pleaſed the audience. He aſſayed to turne al mennes
myndes. From hearing this cauſe, as it whiche was already ſufficiently
knowen. The ſuttel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ies and craftes where with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes are wont to creepe
into mennes heartes, he applied to vs. Calling vs foxes, and dogges. And at the
laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that we ought to be reiected, and referred, to the counſel
of Trent, which the Pope of Rome had proclaymed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that we ſhould
haue free comming thither, and the Popes ſafeconduyte, that there the
controuerſies of fayth &amp; religion ought to be iudged, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which,
weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſouldiors or other not exerciſed in diuine matters, were not mete to
be iudges. Thus as it were, perſwading <pb facs="tcp:11319:62"/> the Queene, he willed
her to ſend vs to Trent. Hitherto his talke, although it fauored bitter hate,
and malice, yet to ſome ſemed graue and ſeuere. But at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> laſte, he
played the foole ſo kindly, as if it had ben in a ſtage. For when he
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes Supper, &amp; promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a playne ſimilitude to
proue the preſence therein, he ſayd it was euen lyke, as if any Prince,
when he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued victory on his enemies, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the remembraunce
therof, would inſtitute yearly playes, whereby bothe his warre, and victory
might be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to al mennes eyes. And if any man in thoſe playes
ſhoulde repreſente the perſon of the Prynce, That would ſo much the
more moue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beholders, to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber it, but if y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> king
himſelf would be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſhew hymſelfe there, then theſame
would be moſt noble and excellent. Euen ſo ſayd he, that Chriſt
himſelfe, when he inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the remembraunce of his paſſion would
alſo be preſent, and in the ſame. About the ende of hys oration he
aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to enflame the Queene agaynſt vs, <pb facs="tcp:11319:63"/> and made many
mournfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaintes faining himſelfe to wepe, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thoſe
ieſters, which ar common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apte to counterfayte any geſture. Hereto Beza
aunſwered, that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard talked, as though we were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy conuict of
hereſy. But for aſmuchas no man hitherto, hath ſhewed vs oure error, he
might haue done much better, if he had reſerued, the ſcoffes which he
beſtowed on vs, to hymſelfe and his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. Bicauſe we can not ſe how
they touche vs. And as to his councel, that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Queenes maieſtie was not ſo
bare of counſell, that ſhe neded it. But that ſhe and her councell ſawe
well inough, what is beſt to be done, and by what meanes, they may prouide
for common quietneſſe. But that which he ſayd of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſupper,
that he made nothing els of, than a play of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hiſtory of Chriſt
(bicauſe it was to blaſphemous &amp; beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) beyng ouerpaſſed, he
turned toward maſter Spenſa. He vrged the playne wordes of the Lord. Thys
is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the conſent of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes, whiche nothing differ
therein. We aunſwered that theſame Euangeliſtes <pb facs="tcp:11319:63"/> ſayd,
thys is my bloud of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And an other. Thys cup is the new
Teſtament, in my bloud. Whych without a figure can not be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
And hereby it appeareth, that it is a Sacramental maner of ſpeach. Which
Auſtine teacheth moſt plainly in his .xxiii. Epiſtle to Boniface. If the
Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes (quoth he) had not a certayne lykeneſſe, of thoſe thynges,
wherof thei are Sacramentes, they wer no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes at al. Of thys
lykeneſſe moſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly, they take the names of thoſe thyngs, wherof
they are Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Lyke as therfore, after a certayne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Sacrament
of the body of Chriſt is the body of Chriſt, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
bloud of Chriſt, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of chriſt, ſo is alſo the Sacrament of
fayth, faith it ſelfe. But Spenſa ſayde that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> letted not, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we
ought ſimply, &amp; without figure to credite the wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. We
ſayd: that a Sacramentall maner of ſpeache, coulde not be withoute fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.
But if there be a figure in our Sacramentes (quoth Spenſa) they ſhal not
then muche differ, from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which
<pb facs="tcp:11319:64"/> are altogether figuratine. And we ſay, that they were a figure
and ſhadowe of that truthe, which was fulfilled to vs in Chriſt.
Otherwiſe, we muſt nedes confeſſe, that they were figures of a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.
Which is moſt vnreaſonable, we denyed that conſequence, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, appointed by God in the olde Teſtament, are referred to the truth
it ſelfe, wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers wer partakers, but a farre of, before the
commynge of Chriſt. But we are nye at hande. After he was offred for vs.
Neither do we ſay that we are as yet vnder figures, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we nede yet, as
long as we lyue in this body, viſible ſignes and Sacraments, and in them we
ſay ther are figuratiue or Sacramentall maners of ſpeache, which
neuertheleſſe proueth not, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we haue the truthe, notwithſtandinge,
theſe ſignes. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude we agree with Bernarde ſaying.<note place="margin">Bernard. ſermone .xxxiii. ſuꝑ
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antica,</note> The truth is ſet
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me: but in a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The Angel is fed with the meale of the corne,
or the perfect grayne. But I muſt be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with the barke of the
Sacramentes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of his fleſh, with the chaffe of the letter, and
the cloke of fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:64"/>But ſure, howſoeuer theſe be tempered and
ſwetened, with the aboundaſice of ſpirit and fayth, certainly the barke
of the Sacrament, and the fine boulted meale of the corne, fayth and hope,
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, and preſence, eternity &amp; preſent tyme, the countenaunce
&amp; the glaſſe, the ymage of God, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of a ſeruaunt, are not
like pleaſaunt in caſt. Wherby it is well proued, that we truely are made
partakers of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truthe, but do not yet fully enioy theſame, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe oure
weakeneſſe requireth the Sacramente, the barke and the cloke. After thys
communication with Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa was ended, there ſtepte vp an other doctoure,
one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sorboniſtes, vrging agayne. By a ſuttel and crafty meanes as he
thought hymſelfe the expoſition of theſe the Lordes wordes. This is my
body, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he aſked what we thought was meant by thys pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, (hoc)
we aunſwered that bread was meant ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, and that the body was ſpeken
ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> therby we might wel perceine y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the bread is a ſigne of
the body. They on the contrary ſyde: Sayd y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. (Hoc) is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
neutre gender, &amp; can <pb facs="tcp:11319:65"/> not by the rules of Grammer, be
refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the bread, but was induuduum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum. And onely to note the body,
as if a man ſhould ſaye. This is oyle. This is hony. Thys is a building.
And ſuche lyke. Therein imitating Durand. Whom Gardyner alſo an open
ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye of the Ghoſpell, and alleaged by them, dyd folowe. We ſhewed, that
that repugned wyth the nature of a Sacramente, foraſmuche as, if it lacke a
ſigne, if it be brought to nothynge, or made as nothyng, it ceaſſeth to
bee a Sacrament. And it is a great maruell that none of the olde fathers could
ſee thys fiction of induuduum vagum. But thys ſatiſfied them not. And
therefore repeating theſame continually, wyth great cryes, they ceaſſed
not after the maner of the Sorboniſtes, to babble til nyght. Yea and one of
them, fooliſhlye &amp; impudently threatned Beza. Saying: Oh, I would we had
thee within oure colledge. We in the meane tyme eyther helde our peace, or
modeſtly obiected certayne argumentes, til the noiſe wer whuſſhed, but
bicauſe they wuld nedes eyther wynne, or ſeeme to wynne, with <pb facs="tcp:11319:65"/>
trifeling or loude crying, we preuayled nothyng. Wherefore to be ſhorte, we
ſayd, that all the auncient fathers made with vs, and we woulde be iudged by
them. Neither did we depart, tyll the Cardinal pronuſed vs, to ſende vnto
vs the authoritie of Auſtene, &amp; other aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, whereby oure
opinion is condemned. But we could neuer haue them. He meant hereafter to
conferre by wrytyng, bicauſe he ſaw that by our talke, God opened the eares
of many, but chiefely of the nobles. Afterwardes the order of our diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
was altered. For there were fyue choſen to conferre with vs, and thoſe
ſuch as paſſed all the reſte, in learning, witte, and modeſtye.
Monluke the Byſhop of Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Sigenſis an other Biſhop, the
Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of Saligne, the Abbot of Botillery, and doctor Spenſa. Agaynſt
thoſe wer choſen on our part, doctor Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir, Theodore Beza.
Auguſtine Harlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Iohn Spina. Nicholas Gallaſius We agreed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
order, place, tyme, and ſecretaryes, whyche ſhoulde regyſter the
queſtions propoſed, and the reaſons on eyther part.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:66"/>And then the ſelfe ſame day, which was the laſt
of September, we began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate with what order we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the
diſputation. We wiſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, that we might orderly proſecute
euery article of our confeſſion. Whiche requeſt to be reaſonable they
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues confeſſed, ſaying that they coulde not allow that
proſperous order, that began at the laſt, yet bicauſe we were alreadye
entred into that article, they thought it good to finiſh it, afore we came to
the reſt.</p>
            <p>Therfore the next daye at oure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, we entreated of the
preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt in his Supper. The Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bote of Saluine,
brought forth a place out of an auncient Greke copy of Ciri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus a Biſhop of
Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherof there was no long reaſoning, bicauſe it made much with
vs. At the laſt, after muche alteration we concluded thus. That in that
reſpect, that fayth makes thoſe thynges preſente, that are promyſed,
&amp; that ſame fayth, doth moſte truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the body and bloud, of
our Lorde Ieſus chriſt, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt, <pb facs="tcp:11319:66"/> in
that reſpecte, we confeſſe the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his body and bloude in his
holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in the whiche he offereth, giueth, and exhibyteth, trulye the
Subſtauce of hys body, and bloude, by the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of hys holye Spirite.
And we doe receiue &amp; eate, ſpyritually and by ſayth that very body,
whiche dyed for vs, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we may be bones of hys bones, &amp; fleſhe of his
fleſhe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby we may be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; receyue whatſoeuer is
neceſſary to our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A copye of this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thoſe that
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerred with vs, gaue to the reſt of the byſhops and doctours y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were
at Poyſſye. But they alowed it not, wherefore, the nexte daye, another was
propoſed vs, wherein there was ſomewhat chaunged. For that whiche we
attribute to fayth, it attributed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde. That when we perceiued was done
of purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it beyng left doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, euery man might interprete the
ſenſe therof at his pleſure, leaſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould therby be deceiued,
we woulde by no meanes admitte for, foraſmuche as we came together there, to
prouide for the quietnes of our conſcience, we endeuoured, as muche as laye
in vs <pb facs="tcp:11319:67"/> to withſtand all error and doubte. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles, leaſt
we ſhould ſeeme to ſtick vppon wordes, we were contented, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they
ſhoulde chaunge the forme of the wryting, ſo they altered nothing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſenſe. This forme therfore that folowes they thought better, and promiſed
to moue all the byſhops to agre there to. We doe confeſſe, that Chriſte
in hys holy ſupper, doth truly offer, gyue, &amp; exhibite, the ſubſtance
of hys body and bloud, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> operacion of the holy ghoſt: and that we
receyue, and eate, ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentallye, ſpirytually, and by fayth, hys bodye
that died for vs, that we may be bones of his bones, and fleſhe of his
fleſhe. That there by we maye receyue lyfe, and whatſoeuer pertayneth to
our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But foraſmuch as faith grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vppon the worde of god,
doth make thoſe thyngs preſente, whiche are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed: by thys fayth we
acknowledge, that we trulye, and verelye, receyue the true and naturall bodye
of oure lorde Ieſus Chriſte, by the vertue of the holy ghoſt. In this
reſpect, we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye &amp; bloude, of oure
lorde, &amp; ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt, in his ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11319:67"/>All thoughe thys forme litle differed from the other,
yet they hoped that it woulde be better alowed of the lordes. And therfore they
toke it with them, to communicate vnto them. We ſayde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we woulde in lyke
maner, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it with oure brethren, and reſerue oure ſelues
libertye, either to adde or expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any thinge therin, as we ſhould thinke
good.</p>
            <p>When the Cardinalles had ſene this forme, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
allowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it very well &amp; reioyced, as though we were tourned to them. And
diuerſe tales were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon ſprede of vs. But when it was peruſed by
the doctours as well Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boniſts, as others, they lightly chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged their
opinion. They added therto ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, (as we here ſay) their opynion, whereby
they ſhewed, what they thought wanted in it, or wherefore they thought it was
not to be allowed. Alſo, thei made almoſt a Tragedy, betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops,
and thoſe which had conferred with vs, and had put in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> forme of this
agremente of this article, among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as thoughe they did either agree
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, or mocke with them. But bycauſe it is <pb facs="tcp:11319:68"/> no part of my
purpoſe, to writ their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. I will willingly leaue it. And now I
come to the declaration of oure opynion, as concernynge the preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
body of Chriſt in his ſupper, which we reſerued, free to our ſelues,
leaſt any doubtfulnes, bycauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhortnes of our fyrſt writing,
myght breed any doubte or error.</p>
            <p>We affirme, that no diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of place may let our coniunction
with the body and bloude of Chriſt, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſupper, is a
heauenly thinge. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought in the earthe, we receiue with the mouthe of
oure body, the breade &amp; wyne, the true Sacraments, &amp; ſygnes, of the
body and bloud of Chriſt: yet by fayth, &amp; the helpe of the holy ghoſt,
our mindes to whom this foode doth chiefly belonge, caried vp to heauen, feede
on the preſent body &amp; bloude. And in this reſpecte we ſaye alſo,
that the body is ioyned with the breade, and the bloude with the wyne. But no
other wyſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacramentally, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, not accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to place or
ſituatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but bycauſe they do effectuouſly ſignify, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> God giueth it
to thoſe that faythfullye communicate &amp; <pb facs="tcp:11319:68"/> they trulye receiue
it by faythe.</p>
            <p>Hereby it appereth in what ſorte we thinke, of the preſence of
the bodye of Chriſt, in the Vſe and Miniſtration of his Supper. For we
admytte, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tranſubſtantiation nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. Yea we
refuſe all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſence, wherby Chriſtes body is thought to be in the
earth, without qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tity: or is affirmed to be any otherwher than in heauen. We
vſe the name of ſubſtaunce to ſignifye, that we meante not our fayth,
of anye fayned bodye or phantaſme, neyther of the vertue only of Chriſts
paſſion, or his merites only (which neuertheleſſe, we confeſſe to
be the ſpirituall catyng of Chriſtes fleſhe) but euen of the true and
natural bodye of the ſonne of God, which he toke of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> virgin Mary, and
afterwards was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and raiſed again for vs, and now reſteth in
heauen, till ſuche tyme as yt ſhal com to iudge the quick &amp; the
dead.</p>
            <p>And this was the ende of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For they that conferred
with vs beyng yll intreated of theyre fellowes, came not agayne. Neyther were
anye other choſen in theyr roomes. Neyther <pb facs="tcp:11319:69"/> ſince that tyme,
dyd the Biſhoppes ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefy any thing vnto vs, but though we oftentimes
deſired, that we myght goe forwardes, &amp; handle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, that wer yet
vntouched, we could vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of their mindes therin, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they
min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to depart, &amp; wer deſirous to referre all thinges, to the councell
of Trente. Therefore, ordre being taken for the leauiyng of a ſubſedy
(wherof perhaps they were more careful, than of anye thing els,) &amp;
deliuering vp to the King the articles, whereof they had agreed among
themſelues, not making anye accompte of vs, but leauing vs in the court, they
al repaired to their homes.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Paules Churchyarde, by Luke
Harryſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11319:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
